<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penitent murderer. Being an exact narrative of the life and death of Nathaniel Butler; who (through grace) became a convert, after he had most cruelly murdered John Knight. With the several conferences held with the said Butler in Newgate, by the Right Honorable the Lord Maior, and several eminent ministers, and others. As also his confession, speech, prayer, and the sermon preached after his execution; with several useful admonitions, and excellent discourses. / Collected by Randolph Yearwood, chaplain to the Right Honorable, the Lord Major of the city of London.</title>
            <author>Yearwood, Randolph, d. 1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1660_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867918</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867918</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 208:E1660[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penitent murderer. Being an exact narrative of the life and death of Nathaniel Butler; who (through grace) became a convert, after he had most cruelly murdered John Knight. With the several conferences held with the said Butler in Newgate, by the Right Honorable the Lord Maior, and several eminent ministers, and others. As also his confession, speech, prayer, and the sermon preached after his execution; with several useful admonitions, and excellent discourses. / Collected by Randolph Yearwood, chaplain to the Right Honorable, the Lord Major of the city of London.</title>
                  <author>Yearwood, Randolph, d. 1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 80, [24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Newcomb for J. Rothwell at the Fountain in Goldsmiths-Row in Cheapside, and Tho. Matthews at the White-horse in the New Buildings in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes letters of Nathaniel Butler, and discourse by several ministers concerning the death of Butler.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 14.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Butler, Nathaniel, d. 1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Knight, John, d. 1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Murder --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Penitent Murderer.</hi> BEING AN Exact Narrative Of the Life and Death of <hi>NATHANIEL B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TLER;</hi> Who (through Grace) became a Convert, after he had moſt cruelly murdered <hi>JOHN KNIGHT.</hi> With the ſeveral Conferences held with the ſaid <hi>Butler</hi> in <hi>Newgate,</hi> by the Right Honorable the LORD MAIOR, and ſeveral eminent Miniſters, and others. As alſo his Confeſſion, Speech, Prayer, and the Sermon preached after his Execution; with ſeveral uſeful Admonitions, and excellent Diſcourſes. <hi>Collected by</hi> RANDOLPH YEARWOOD, <hi>Chaplain to the Right Honorable, the Lord Major of the City of</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut 13.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And all Iſrael ſhall hear, and fear, and ſhall do no more any ſuch wickedneſs as this is among you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Newcomb</hi> for <hi>J. Rothwell</hi> at the Fountain in <hi>Goldſmiths-Row</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Matthews</hi> at the White-horſe in the New Buildings in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the city of London</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>London, <date>Saturday Sept. <hi>12. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis is that Exact Narrative concerning <hi>Nathaniel But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> which was ſome time ſince promiſed to come forth by my appointment, under the hand of <hi>Randolph Yearwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Robert Tichborne,</hi> Major.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROBERT TICHBORNE K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>,</hi> Lord Major of the City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You have done (being directed, and enabled from on high) many noble and good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for this City, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof is yet yours. But really (my Lord) the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable act was this, your perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb facs="tcp:170235:4"/>and frequent viſiting <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Butler,</hi> when he lay a priſoner in <hi>Newgate.</hi> His ſoul certainly was precious in your eyes; and this engaged you to ſend others, and to go your ſelf to ſee him ſeveral times: I verily believe you will ſee him yet once more; not as a Malefactor in an obſcure diſparaging Goal, but as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God in the Kingdom of Chriſt, whither (I am confident) he is gone, and you are going. Before he went, he deſired me to give you humble thanks for all the favor he had received from you, or by your means from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: He was very thankfull to your Lordſhip, and the reſt
<pb facs="tcp:170235:4"/>of the Honorable Bench, for his Fortnights Reprieval; confeſſing that Court to be both juſt, and merciful; Juſt, in condemning his body to death; and merciful, in ſparing his life for ſome weeks after the Sentence, upon deſign to ſave his ſoul: And truly you may ſafely conclude, that his ſoul is ſafe. And is not ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion a rich Requital of all your Exhortations, Tears, and Prayers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> I ſhall rejoice to ſee you grow and abound yet more and more in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Holineſs, and (as the Elect of God) bowels of Mercies:
<pb facs="tcp:170235:5"/>which will render you like unto, and well liked of by the <hi>LORD of Lords.</hi> To whom I leave you, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's Servant, <hi>RANDOLPH YEARWOOD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:5"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Malefactor mentioned in this following Narrative was none of mine acquaintance, till (for his horrid fact) he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and impriſoned. So that it was not any Relation of mine to him that put me upon this publication; but I undertook this work, as judging it of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral concernment to all men both good and bad.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the bad. If thou art an evil wicked man er woman, then this Narrative (with the annexed admonitions and ſermon <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) much concern thee, to make thee (if poſſible) penitent and truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Art thou a gracious, good man, or woman; then thou haſt reaſon to rejoyce on carth, as God
<pb facs="tcp:170235:6"/>himſelf and the Angels of God rejoyce in heaven ever one repenting ſinner, <hi>Luke 15.7. and 10.</hi> I doubt not but thou wilt be well ſatisfied by the following Lines concerning the true conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a very hainous Offendor.</p>
            <p>Now (good Reader) grant me one requeſt, not to look upon the following Diſcourſes as a bare ſtory or a piece of News, and ſo having read and ſeen it, there is an end: But read and conſider, read and pray that this great and extraordinary paſſage of divine Providence may profit thy Soul, which is the deſire of my heart and Soul, to God himſelf. Otherwiſe I could not be (as indeed I am) thy Well-wiſher,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Friend and Servant, RANDOLPH YEARWOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:6"/>
            <head>Three Conferences held with <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> (during his Impriſonment) by the Right Honorable the Lord Major, under his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips own hand.</head>
            <p>WHen <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> was firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and brought before me, he was in exceeding great burden of Spirit, full of tears, free to confeſs the Fact, with all the aggravations thereof, and was ſollicitous for nothing, but a few days reſpit for his poor Soul, it ſeeming to me that nothing at that time was on his thoughts, but what ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his Soul.</p>
            <p>At my firſt Conference with him which was about five or ſix days after his Condemnation, I found him very ready to acknowledge his actual ſins, and to charge himſelf with them and the aggravations that did accompany
<pb facs="tcp:170235:7"/>them, and this with ſad tears of complaint, and indignation againſt himſelf and his ſins; but did take no notice of his ſinful Nature; Which my ſelf and a Friend with me (Mr <hi>Grif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fith</hi> of the Charter houſe) perceiving, We en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by Scripture to ſhew him his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nature, as the Root of all his ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he diligently hearkened to, and was affected with, but acknowledged his former Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance herein, and that he had not ſo expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before thougth hereof, or been inſtructed hereabout, and what he heard and received at this time among other Particulars, was ſo far bleſt, and wrought into his ſoul, that to our ſelves, and (as we heard) to others, he did from that Night following much inſiſt upon and bemoan his ſinful nature, and the ſtate of ſin he was born in, as well as, or together with thoſe ſinful acts he was guilty of.</p>
            <p>At my ſecond being with him, after apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the free grace of God and Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to his faith for the pardon of his ſins; I asked him whether his heart could moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly receive that pardon, or a pardon for his life, and bid him conſider, and tell me what his heart ſaid in that Point: After a little pauſe, he made me this Anſwer, That indeed he did not deſire to live longer in this world, for he had found ſin ſo bitter a thing, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:170235:7"/>ſo prone to ſin, that if he ſhould live lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſin againſt God, it would be much more bitter to him then death, and he did heartily Bleſſe God that had brought him to the hand of Juſtice, and did truly love the party, who (as he thought) was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to diſcover him, acknowledging that the Devil had tempted him to lay violent hands on himſelf; and after that temptation to fly beyond the Sea; which if God had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him to do, and ſo eſcaped Juſtice, he might have gone on in his former courſe of ſin without Repentance, but did truly bleſs God that had delivered him from theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations; and had brought him to that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that then he was in, he did acknowledge with much thankfulneſs to God man, the mercy of a few days between death and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that God had given him ſo great a ſhare in the hearts and prayers of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he did ſeveral times throw himſelf on the free grace of God in the blood and merits of Jeſus Chriſt alone for his Salvation, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all but Chriſt, acknowledging that he beleeved to be waſhed from his bloody Fact, and all his other ſins, by no means but by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>At my third and laſt time of being with
<pb facs="tcp:170235:8"/>him, which was the night before he died, I indeavoured to hold forth to his faith from Scripture, the glorious ſtate in heaven to all Eternity, that Jeſus Chriſt had purchaſed and was in the poſſeſſion of for true believers, and into which ſuch ſouls ſhould immediatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when they leave the body, and abide there with Chriſt their Head for ever: To which he gave very great heed and attention, and though his lips ſaid little, yet to my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion his ſoul ſpake very much, for it wrought in his body, as if it were raiſed up by Faith; through what was held out to him, even to the admiring of that grace and glory; The working of his ſoul, was mixt with Tears (as I conceive) of Joy; for he mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing of the fear of Death, though he was often minded of it, how neer it was at hand, nor did I then perceive any paleneſs in his face, or ſinking of Spirit, (the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of the fear of Death;) But that thoſe workings of his Soul were reachings after that glorious Inheritance held out in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>To be heirs of God, joynt heirs with Chriſt,</hi> which Scripture was then opened to him: And that glorious inheritance ſet forth by the concurrence of ſeveral other Scriptures, with an indeavour to give him a View by the eye of faith, of that which in a very few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:170235:8"/>after, his ſoul ſhould to all Eternity be made partaker of in joy and glory with Chriſt in Heaven, which was infinitely more then could be expreſſed or conceived; and this I judge did make his Soul ſo work within him. After ſome time in prayer, I parted with him, and almoſt the laſt words I had from him were theſe, He told me, he was really offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with himſelf, becauſe he hated ſin no more, which had cauſed him to offend God ſo much; he told me Satan was buſie to perſwade him, That all his Faith and Repentance was falſe, but he had beleeved the Divel too long, and he would truſt him no longer, but now caſt his eternal ſoul on the free grace of God in the Blood of Chriſt alone for Salvation, renouncing himſelf wholly. In this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and frame of Spirit I left him: And as I am informed, (through the free grace of God) he did abide and increaſe in it to his laſt breath. Upon the whole, I am truly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from that Work of God that I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be wrought in him, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of it, that though his former life was full of all wickedneſs, his ſoul exceeding ignorant of God, and his own ſinful nature all that time, and his Repentance and Faith in Chriſt very late, yet that the free grace of God (who is not bounded to time) did make
<pb facs="tcp:170235:9"/>both his Faith and Repentance true, and do beleeve he is with Chriſt in glory. I do not give this Publike Atteſt to encourage ſin, but to magnifie the free grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt to Sinners, and I do aſſure whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads this, that poor ſoul which is the Subject of it, found ſin to be exceeding bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before he had any taſt of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods free grace in Chriſt. Hoping this may be of Publike Uſe, I am free to Atteſt it with my Name. <hi>September</hi> 10. 1657.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Robert Tichborne,</hi> Major.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:9"/>
            <head>A brief Account of a Viſit given to <hi>Nathaniel Butler,</hi> a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate</hi> upon, the Friday before he ſuffered, by <hi>Tho. Caſe,</hi> a Miniſter of the City of <hi>London;</hi> wherein he made theſe following Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</head>
            <p>THE ſaid <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> expreſſed, 1. A deep ſenſe of that deſperate Bloody fact which he had committed, which he loaded with all the blackeſt aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations that might be; eſpecially with this Conſideration; <hi>That for ought he knew, he had deſtroyed body and ſoul with oue blow: He had begg'd and obtained a space of Repentance from his Judges, but had not afforded his Brother one moment to beg pardon at the hand of God.</hi> This Conſideration ſtuck ſo deeply upon his ſpirit, that it had well nigh ſunk him into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, had not God ſent in ſome relief by the hand of one that viſited him in priſon, in the
<pb facs="tcp:170235:10"/>inſtance of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> who having ſacrificed his ſons unto Devils, and ſhed much other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, upon his repentance finding mercy, did not deſpairingly afflict himſelf with the conſideration of what became of the ſouls of thoſe whom he had ſo cruelly murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Secret things belong unto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He expreſt not only ſenſe of the guilt of Blood, but a right Goſpel-notion of the <hi>ſinfulneſs of ſin; All ſin,</hi> the leaſt ſin, not as deſtroying only, but as defiling; not as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Creature in the effects of it, but as contrary to God in the nature of it; A grieving of the Spirit; a crucifying of Jeſus Chriſt afreſh; a moſt unworthy requital of the love of a crucified Saviour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He diſcovered alſo that, which indeed was the thing which I came purpoſely to the Priſon to enquire after, <hi>viz.</hi> A right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of <hi>Original ſin,</hi> the <hi>Corruption of his Nature,</hi> which he lookt upon as the Fountain and Spring-head of his Murder, Theft, and all other actual wickedneſſ bewailing them all with <hi>David,</hi> in their firſt ſource and ſpring; <hi>Behold, I was born in ſin, and in iniquity did my mother conceive me,</hi> Pſ. 51.5.</p>
            <p>In a word, He had as right a notion of
<pb facs="tcp:170235:10"/>the ſtate of Unregeneracie, as ever I found in any new Convert.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He expreſt alſo an high appretiation of Jeſus Chriſt; not only for pardon of ſin, but for power againſt ſin; not only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the ſoul from the wrath to come, and everlaſting burning, but from the ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; As a Fountain of Holineſs, as well as a Fountain of Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. An high apprehenſion and admiration of Free-grace, in pardoning ſuch a ſinner as he was: Which he expreſt with much ſelf-abhorrencie, as one that had no regard to the Sabbath never acquainted himſelf with the Bible, or Catechiſm, never prayed; And if a good Thought were entring his heart, he would thruſt it away from him with greateſt indignation. The pardon of theſe, with other ſins, he admired in ſome ſuch language as the Apoſtle did, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p n="6">6. God had vouchſafed him a ſweet taſte of the Promiſes; ſome whereof, moſt ſuitable to his condition, God had pitched his ſoul upon, which he repeated with ſo ſweet a reliſh, as a man might perceive his ſoul was even raviſhed with the ſence thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:11"/>
            <p n="7">7. Wonderfully did he bleſs and admire the goodneſs of God in calling ſuch a cruel enemy to mankind as he was, in murdering his Brother, into the prayers, compaſſion, and care of ſo many of his precious Servants, both Miniſters and others. He did particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge the extraordinary pains, care, and tenderneſs of the Chief Magiſtrate of the City, to be beyond all preſident, or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Great affection and compaſſion he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to the ſouls of others: His Fellow-Priſoners profanenefs and deſperate ſecurity he exceedingly lamented; the ignorance and blindnefs of many that came to ſee him, he heartily bewailed; They would aggravate his bloody fact, and ask him whether the ſight of the Bags were not the firſt temptation to the murdering of his Brother? But alas! ſaid he, it was not the ſight of the bags, nor the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil, that could have put me upon ſuch a wickedneſs, had there not been a curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nature within me, by means whereof I was a Murderer before ever I ſlew my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and an Adulterer, and a Blaſphemer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, he ſaid he looked upon that original corruption he carried about him, a greater ſin before God, then a thouſand acts of murder, of adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe it is the fountain of
<pb facs="tcp:170235:11"/>them all; which I never ſaw, ſaid he, or took notice of till now that God hath opened mine eyes in this wonderful manner. Neither do the moſt of men and women ſee it; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the reſtraining power of God; they live free from ſuch groſs and ſcandalous crimes, they think themſelves in a good eſtate, and that they ſhall be ſaved: But alas, ſaid he, they have the ſame nature that I had, and until their natures are changed and renewed, they are accounted as guilty of all ſins before God, and as uncapable of Heaven and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if they had committed them in the greateſt act; this ignorance of the generality of people, old and young he bewailed with much hearty ſence and feeling.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He was very firm and fixed to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Proteſtant Religion, though he had but newly ſuckt them in: Inſomuch that being ſeveral times encountred in Priſon by ſome Prieſts and other Papiſts, that came to ſeduce this poor dying Wretch, who told him that if he would be reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> and turn Catholique (as they call it) they has power to pardon abſolve him (which his Miniſters had not) and that if he would not renounce his Religion, there was no way with him but damnation; with divers ſuch menaces
<pb facs="tcp:170235:12"/>to terrifie him, and flatteries to enſnare him: Yet the Young-man, through grace, ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all theſe Temptations, as a Rock that could not be moved, but ſent them away with a great deal of contempt and indignation. He wiſht the Civil Magiſtrate would be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and reſtrain the liberty, and prevent the temptations of theſe Seducers; which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make his humble requeſt to them at his death.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He did not at all doubt of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation through Free-grace, the merits and love of Jeſus Chriſt; though withall he did make it a very ſolemn Query, Whether he might warrantably and ſafely caſt himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Jeſus Chriſt, on ſuch terms as God holds him forth in the Goſpel to poor loſt Sinners, being ſuch a Sinner as he had been?</p>
            <p n="11">11. He was not at all afraid of death, nor deſirous to live; but being asked by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ſtood by, what he would do if he ſhould live? he anſwered, He deſired not life if he might have it; partly becauſe he durſt not truſt his own heart; partly out of an infinite deſire he had to be with Chriſt, who had loved ſuch a loveleſs wretch as he was.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:12"/>
            <p>One expreſſion he uſed was, <hi>That he was not at all angry with his ſin for bringing him to ſuch a ſhameful end, the ſhame and death do not in the least trouble me.</hi> He was above all theſe conſiderations, and deſired that God might be glorified in, and by his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And laſtly, He earneſtly deſired them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to joyn in prayer with him, which was performed by a Miniſter, who was witneſs to this part of the Narative. He expreſt ſtrong affections, and workings of ſpirit during prayer, and much thankfulneſs for that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian office.</p>
            <p>In many of theſe particulars, poſſibly his very expreſſions <hi>in terminis,</hi> may not be ſo exactly rendred; but a to the import and ſubſtance of every particular, this is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true relation.</p>
            <p>In all he ſpake, the manner of his ſpeech and countenance expreſt the higheſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that might be.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. CASE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:13"/>
            <head>Certain Obſervations of <hi>Thomas Parſon,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Micheal Wood-ſtreet</hi> London.</head>
            <p>BEing deſired to preach at <hi>Newgate,</hi> Aug. 30. in the Afternoon (being the Lords day immediately preceding the Execution of <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi>) I carefully obſerved him while preaching, and had diſcourſe with him both before and after Sermon.</p>
            <p>While preaching, I took notine, that the man ſeemed wholly taken up with what he heard, not minding the great crowd about him, that came to ſee a poor reed ſhaken with the wind, ſtaring him in the face as a condemned Malefactor; but he minded the Pardon I in the Name of God offered him, (treating of the Pardoning Grace of God) with ſo fixed an eye frequently did he look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and ſo heedfully turn to Scriptures, as one taken up with the weightieſt matters, when as otherwiſe it might have wrought ſom diſcompoſure, to have ſo many ſuch Obſervers.</p>
            <p>When with him before and after Sermon, I took notice both of his carriage and Words, by both which, great diſcovery of the frame and temper of his mind might be made.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:13"/>
            <p>His Carriage to my Obſervant and Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall apprehenſion ſeemed to be excellently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered to his preſent condition, being ſweetly ſubmiſſive, neither ſervilely dejected under the Apprehenſions of his paſt ſins and preſent ſtate, nor forwardly confident as though he forgot he were ſuch a Malefactor: His deportment did in my Judgment (not without ſome admiration, then, &amp; after in the reviewing thoughts of it, of the <hi>Decorum</hi> and ſuitableneſs of it to his preſent condition) ſpeak a well mixed and compounded ſence of his own deſerts, and divine mercy; which alſo did his Words.</p>
            <p>His Words might be reduced to theſe two main and excellent heads,</p>
            <p>A declamation againſt ſin, and Admiration of Grace.</p>
            <p>Agrainſt Sin he expreſſed the greateſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicency and abhorrency, yea the Sin of his Nature, that Root of bitterneſs, which he ſaid men took but little notice of: and for actuall Sin abſtractedly from the fruit of it, even ſin as againſt the holy, juſt, and good law of God, and as againſt God that had deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better at his hands, Profeſſing that (as in general he had no deſire to live) ſo if the greateſt hier ſhould be offered him to live, if it might occaſion his return unto folly, he
<pb facs="tcp:170235:14"/>would not accept of life, and the World with it; And that Sin as Sin, even the leaſt. Sin did make his heart riſe at firſt thought of it, and he could ſpit it out with deteſtation, wondring that men made no more of Sin, bewailing he was no more ſenſible of and humbled for Sin, expreſſing how affraid he was now of doing any thing might offend God, even in the leaſt. Then (as all along) he was ready to take all occaſions of a full, free, and impartial confeſſion of Sins, cloathing them with their agravating Circumſtances, to make them out of meaſure ſinfull.</p>
            <p>His high admiring thoughts of the Love and Grace of God, ſeveral ways he expreſſed in a moſt ſerious affectionate manner, both in generall, and in reference to himſelf, and his ſence of his intereſt in them. He was much in Repetition with thankful wonderment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proomiſes of God; ſome I had before ſpoken of in preaching, and ſome others, ſuch as ſet forth Gods readineſs to pardon; the freeneſs, largeneſs, and unchangeableneſs of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning mercy of God; and again and again ſpeaking in the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> And that ſuch an one as I ſhould obtain mercy! Such an one as I find mercy! Admiring the diſtinguiſhing grace of God towards him, that when other Priſoners (though in leſſe danger then himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:170235:14"/>of Death, whom we then heard above make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a noiſe) were without thought of Sin or God, God ſhould ſnatch him as a Fire-brand, and that in ſuch a way, making ſin, ſo great ſin to be overruled to his great good. He expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his appretiating thoughts of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſavourly deſcanting upon them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably applying them to himſelf, ſaying, I could formerly find no thing deſirable in a Promiſe or any Word of God, it was a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to me, but now that the promiſes were the rejoycing of his heart. He ſaid, Satan had ſorely winowed and buffeted him, but Chriſt was on his ſide: And uſing the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>This is our rejoycing, the Teſtimony of our Conſciences,</hi> he added, God hath ſaid, whoſoever repenteth and beleeveth ſhall find mercy and be ſaved; my Conſcience telleth me and witneſſeth to me that I unfeignedly repent, and really beleeve in Chriſt, and I am one of thoſe <hi>Whoſoever;</hi> therefore Chriſt is mine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As to his Condition in general, from what I found or otherwiſe heard, I conceive, there are many things very remarkable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to his ſin committted. 1. That this great Sin was clearly a judiciall ſin, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of former Sins, for which God left him. 2. That as it was the deſerved fruit of a bad Cauſe, ſo it was the accidentall cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:170235:15"/>of good fruit, the Lord overſhooting Satan in his own bow, when and by what meanes he took to make ſure of him, God ſtartled and rouſed Conſcience, which would not with the noiſe of leſſe guilt be awaked, and humbled the Sinner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſeemeth to me very obſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as to the Work of God upon him, that it was ſo orderly gradual; he being firſt bound up partly through his ignorance in which he had been brought up, partly through the amazing guilt that with an overwhelming ſtupifying power came upon him; he afterwards by degrees, and that at laſt to ſuch a meaſure of clearneſs and diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Underſtanding in the things of God, had an extraordinary beam of divine light darted into his Soul: and that by degrees, his ſence of the ſinfulneſs of ſin increaſed (as I have been credibly informed) to a deep humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, not without horror, and ſo ingenious confeſſion: And then upon the alone, and moſt ſufficient foundation of the rich and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes of the Goſpel, he was raiſed up to the apprehenſion of mercy, and at laſt of his particular intereſt in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The hand of the Lord upon the hearts of his People, Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and other Chriſtians in ſome meaſure evidencing the
<pb facs="tcp:170235:15"/>thoughts of God towards the poor man, to be thoughts of Peace and good-will: In that favour he (ſo high an Offendor) found to have time of repentance and reconciliation, who himſelf gave none to his Friend: In the means afforded him, and manifold helps for his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual advantage, which he, in my hearing took notice of with admiring thankfulneſs; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Viſits, generall pitty of Gods people, in the importunate enlarged fervency of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Chriſtians in praying for him, ſcarcely to be parallel'd in the memory of men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: PARSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:16"/>
            <head>Some PaſſAges between <hi>Nath. But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and a Friend of his that came to viſit him, which have been omitted in the other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw do you Nathautel?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>N. Butler,</speaker>
               <p>Very well bleſſed be God; only I muſt tell you, that even now here were with me ſome Popiſh Ladies, who asked me concerning my Faith, and what Religion I did intend to die in: I told them in the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> They anſwered, if I died not in the Roman Catholick Religion, I could not be ſaved, and preſt it with ſeveral Arguments. Pray inform me therefore what is this Popiſh Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is ſuch a Religion, that dares not truſt in Chriſt alone: without mingling their own merits, with the merits of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nath.</speaker>
               <p>That is ſaddeſt Religion in the world for me; I ſhall never be of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! (clapping his hand on his breſt) for I am
<pb facs="tcp:170235:16"/>the vileſt wretch that lives: I have not a good thought to truſt to: I muſt be ſaved only by the merits of Chriſt, if ever I be ſaved.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>The ſame Friend watching with him, the night before he dyed, wiſhed him to think of the free mercy of God in Jeſus Chriſt, that God ſhould call him at the eleventh hour. He anſwered, I deſire to be vile in mine own eyes, and admire free grace.</p>
            <p>About five of the clock that morning he was to ſuffer death, he was raiſed to a high pitch of joy, and cried out, Oh ſirs, help me! Help me to glorifie God! ſhew me how to do it! I cannot do it enough! I cannot contain my ſelf! yet ſuſpecting himſelf, he asked thoſe about him, Was it ſo with you? and with you, when God wrought on you?</p>
            <p>They replied, it was. Oh then ſaid he it is right, bleſſed be God: Come let us ſing the 100 Pſalm, which he ſung with much ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity.</p>
            <p>About an hour after they knockt off his ſhackels; now ſaid his Friend, Come <hi>Nat.</hi> now thy ſhackles are off, I will get thee out, and thou ſhalt run thy old courſe, and have money enough, and take thy fill of luſt and pleaſure again:</p>
            <p>He ſeriouſly replied, Really, Really, Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (clapping his hand on his breaſt) if I
<pb facs="tcp:170235:17"/>know my own heart, I would not for ten thouſand worlds loſe the opportunity of this morning. I am now going where I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſin again.</p>
            <p>So leaving the dark Dungeon, wherein he was Priſoner, in order to his execution, he uttered theſe expreſſions to his friends about him; <hi>O this dark Dungeon! The beſt Room that ever I came in; and this contemptible Bed, the beſt that ever I lay in!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170235:17"/>
            <head>AN EXACT NARRATIVE Of the Life and Death of NATHANIEL BUTEER; With the ſeveral Conferences held with him by the Right Honorable the Lord Major, and ſeveral eminent Miniſters; <hi>As alſo his Confeſſions, Speech, Prayer, &amp;c. together with the Sermon preached the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after his Execution.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I enter upon the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, give me leave very briefly to premiſe, how <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> behaved himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Murther committed, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was a very lewd Young man, being addicted to divers ſins, which he himſelf hath freely confeſſed. For inſtance,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He was a great Company-keeper, and given to Gaming very much; whereby he gain'd money, and ſeveral Watches of Young men, one whereof he reſtor'd to the Owner, after his Conſcience was awaked, in priſon</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170235:18"/>
            <p n="2">2. He enticed ſome Servants to purloin from their Maſters, and ſell the Goods; then would he and they go together and ſpend the money among themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He lived in Fornication, frequenting the company and the houſes of Harlots; in ſo much that (as he himſelf under his own hand informed me) he judged, this very ſin of Whoredom did draw him on to that of ſhedding blood. Concerning which fact I ſhall now ſpeak; as alſo concerning his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in Priſon, and at his Execution, being an Eye and Ear-witneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>THis <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> came from <hi>Alton</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> where he was born; and at the time of his Apprehenſion, was an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice with one Mr. <hi>Goodday,</hi> a Drawer of Cloth in <hi>Carter-lane, London;</hi> during which time he became acquainted with one <hi>John Knight,</hi> an Apprentice alſo in the ſame City. Theſe two were much together, but eſpecially when Mr. <hi>Worth</hi> (<hi>John Knight's</hi> Maſter) was gone to <hi>Briſtol</hi>-Fair; then did theſe two young men lie together ſeveral nights at Mr. <hi>Worth's</hi> houſe, at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Milk-ſtreet;</hi> where in the ſhop, on Wedneſday morning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170235:18"/>being the 6. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1657. <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> ſeeing ſome Bags of money, he was thereupon tempted to take away the life of his Friend and Bed-fellow, that he might ſecurely convey away the Money which he had now ſeen in the Till of the ſhop. After they had been abroad that day, at night they lay again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the bloody deſign running ſtill in the mind of <hi>Butler;</hi> he intending about the dead of the night (for ſo he expreſſed himſelf to me) to deſtroy the Young man by cutting his throat: Accordingly he took his knife in his hand, but his heart would not ſuffer him to do it; then he laid down the knife again, yea he took up, and laid down hi sknife ſeveral times (ſo he told me) before he acted his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: But in the morning very early he did indeed fall very violently and inhumanely on the Youth, who lay harmleſly aſleep upon the bed. The firſt wound not being mortal, awaked him, whereupon he ſtrugled and made a noiſe (not conſiderable enough) which was heard into another room of the ſame houſe. Then <hi>Butler</hi> chopt his fiſt into the mouth of the Young man, and ſo they two lay ſtriving and tumbling very near half an houre, before the fatal blow was given; but at length he did moſt barbarouſly murder the Young man, giving him a very ghaſtly deadly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170235:19"/>wound, croſs the throat: And then he went down, taking away out of the ſhop a ſum of money in two bags, being about One hundred and twenty pounds: And ſo with his double guilt of Robbery and Murder, leaving his bloody Shirt behind him, and a Lock of his own Hair in the hand of the dead Young man, which Hair was pull'd off in their ſtriving to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, one to commit, the other to prevent the fact; after he had ſo done, he went to his maſters houſe in <hi>Corter-lane,</hi> where he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately laid the Money in a new Trunk that he bought with part of the Money. This Murderer abode for certain days, that is, from Thurſday to Saturday, at his Maſters houſe unſuſpected, following his buſineſs at home as formerly.</p>
            <p>Many thoughts and jealouſies were work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in men, who ſhould be the Murderer: And in a few days, one in <hi>Milk-ſtreet</hi> (the ſtreet where the Murder was done) knowing that <hi>Butler</hi> uſed ſometimes to be with the Young man who was now murder'd, went to <hi>Butler's</hi> Maſter's houſe in <hi>Carter-lane,</hi> and ſpake with him, by whoſe words and carriage he ſuppoſed he might be guilty, and ſo cauſed him to be apprehended: But yet for ſome ſmall time, the ſaid <hi>Butler</hi> denied the Fact; but at length confeſſed, That he, and he only
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170235:19"/>did it. After his apprehenſion, he was brought before the Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> to whom he declared the Murder, and the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, crying out for a little time for his ſoul, and much lamenting his ſin. That night he was committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and there lay exceedingly ſtartled about the ſtate of his ſoul, ſaying often, <hi>What will become of my poor ſoul! What ſhall I do to be ſaved!</hi> beginning now to ſee the ſinfulneſs of ſin. Whom I may compare to <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> in three reſpects. 1. As to matter of fact; for <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhed much innocent blood, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 21.16. ſo did he ſhed (too much) innocent blood. 2. He ſomething reſembled <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in his impriſonment, mentioned 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 33.11. As <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was taken and bound with fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo was he clapt in the Hole or Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of <hi>Newgate,</hi> with heavy irons about his legs. 3. <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and he were one and the ſame in this ſenſe, that when they were in affliction, they beſought the Lord God, and humbled themſelves greatly before the God of their fathers: For this great Offender could often ſay, <hi>He could never be humbled enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 13 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when he was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned at the Seſſions in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> he pleaded Guilty to the Indictment, with very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170235:20"/>much ſhame, confuſion of face, and ſorrow of heart: And on Friday the 15. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> he demeaned himſelf very humbly before the Bench, heartily ſubmitting to the Sentence of Death that then paſſed upon him, ſaying, <hi>He had deſtroyed the Image of the Eternal GOD;</hi> alluding (as I verily believe) to thoſe words in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. — <hi>For in the image of God, &amp;c.</hi> After his Sentence, he was conveyed back to priſon; penitently acknowledging, that he had neglected the good Word of God, and therefore was the longer kept off (through ignorance of the Goſpel) from cloſing with Chriſt Jeſus. But after a few days diſcourſe with ſeveral Miniſters and others, who opened the Scriptures to him, he began to underſtand (through the grace of God) the Word of Grace. And though he had many good Books brought to him by divers viſiting Friends, yet he chiefly looked into the holy Scriptures themſelves, and found very much advantage, light and peace by theſe following paſſages out of the Old Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Sam. 12.9. Where <hi>Nathan</hi> ſpake ſharply to <hi>David,</hi> for deſpiſing the Commandment of the Lord, to do evil in the ſight of the Lord, in killing <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> the <hi>Hittite</hi> with the ſword — Verſ.13. <hi>David ſaid to Nathan, I have ſinned againſt the Lord; and Nathan ſaid
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170235:20"/>to David, The Lord alſo hath put away thy ſin.</hi> From hence he underſtood the readineſs of God to forgive confeſſing, repenting ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, though they are guilty of innocent blood.</p>
            <p>Job 33.27, 28 <hi>He</hi> (the Lord) <hi>looketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men</hi> (Oh that men would look after the Lord!) <hi>and if ANY ſay, I have ſinned and perverted that which was right, and it profited me not; he</hi> (that is, the Lord) <hi>will deliver his ſoul from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iſa 45.18, 19.— <hi>I ſaid not unto the ſeed of Jacob, ſeek ye me in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iſa. 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him return to the Lord, and he will AB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DANTLY pardon.</hi> The word <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly,</hi> he uſed to pronounce with an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis; for, he ſaw (his eyes being now an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with ſpiritual eye-ſalve) that he had multiplied ſins exceedingly, and that he ſtood in abſolute need of the Lords abundant, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied pardons: whereof he had good hope through this good word of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ezek 18.23. <hi>Have I any pleaſure at all that the wicked ſhould die, ſaith the Lord God, and not that he ſhould return from his wases and live?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170235:21"/>
            <p>30.— <hi>Repent and turn your ſelves from all your tranſgreſſions; SO iniquity ſhall not be your ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>31. <hi>Caſt away from you all your tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, whereby ye have tranſgreſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new spirit; for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>32. <hi>For I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth: wherefore turn your ſelves and live ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ezek. 33.11. <hi>Say unto them, As I live, ſaith the Lord</hi> (here the poor Priſoner would note to his comfort that a repenting ſinner hadnot onely the Word and Promiſe of God for forgiveneſs, but the Oath of God to give ſuch a finner the greater aſſurance of pardon) <hi>I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his ways and live: Turn ye. turn ye</hi> (ſee the importunity of God with poor ſinners for the good of their ſouls) <hi>from your evil ways. For why will ye die O houſe of Iſrael!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Micah 7.18. was a place pleaſant to his ſoul. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the reranant of his heritage? He retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delighteth in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> Verſ. 19. <hi>He will turn again</hi> (as one doth when his anger is gone) <hi>he will have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170235:21"/>compaſſion upon us, he will ſubdue our iniquities, and thou wilt caſt ALL their ſins into the depth of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſhall give you a ſhort Liſt of ſome New Teſtament Texts, whereby the Lord conveyed Counſel and Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this doubting ſtaggering poor Wretch.</p>
            <p>Matth. 18.11. — <hi>For the Son of man is come to ſave that which was loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Joh. 3.14, 15, 16. <hi>And as Moſes lifted up the Serpent in the wilderneſs, even ſo must the Son of Man be lifted up, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in him, ſhould not periſh but have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; For God SO loved the WORLD, that whoſoever</hi> (this word <hi>[whoſoever]</hi> he he ſpake with joy) <hi>beleeveth in him, ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life:</hi> Now (ſaith <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi>) I am one to whom this word ſpeaketh; and therefore God gave the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for my ſoul; I beleeve in him, and therefore I truſt to live eternally through him, according to the gracious terms of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>John 6.37. —<hi>and him that cometh to me I will in no wiſe</hi> (here he would repeat and reiterate theſe words in <hi>NO WISE CAST
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170235:22"/>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T,</hi> in <hi>NO WISE,</hi> in <hi>NO WISE</hi>) <hi>caſt out:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>This a faithful ſaying and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Tim. 2.5, 6. <hi>For there is one God, and one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a ranſom for all to be teſtified in due time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In hearing, reading, and conferring upon theſe (and many more) Scriptures, he would often ſay to me and others, theſe are good Scriptures, brave Scriptures, are they not brave Scriptures? He would make very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and frequent ſearch into his ſoul, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſincerity of his ſorrow, and would not eaſily beleeve that his repentance was true, or that he had right to the precious promiſes of the Goſpel. But by much ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him by many good people, that he would applie Chriſt, and alſo by ſeeking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for a ſpirit of Faith for him, he did begin to act a faith of recumbency and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, being (as he often ſaid) perſwaded that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt was able to ſave to the uttermoſt, and willing to ſave ſuch as come unto God by him; yet he could not come up to that full aſſurance of hope and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170235:22"/>confidence, as he deſired, and we alſo deſired heartily on his behalf. So that ſometimes he would break forth and ſay, How can I that have been gurlty of all ſins whatſoever (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) as Murder, Fornication, Theft, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge or apply a pardon? He was much afraid of running upon either of theſe two Rooks, that is, preſumption or deſpair; I told him that diffidence and deſpair was the ſtrongeſt preſumption againſt God, ſaying to him, Is it not preſumption for a man to diſ: obey God, and not to beleeve him? Now the command of God in his glorious Goſpel is, that men weary of, and heavy laden with ſins ſhould come to Chriſt, that they might find reſt to their ſouls. The deſign of God (ſaid I) in the Scriptures is not to give ſome feeble weak hope of pardon, but a lively hope, and a firm expectation of ſalvation, to all that mourn, and really repent. Which ſo wrought upon him that for the ſpace of ſome daies before his ſuffering death, it pleaſed the God of all comfort to give him joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and ſometimes ſtrong conſolation, inſomuch that he would at times expreſs very great inward gladneſs, which all that knew his former mournings were glad to ſee, and glorified God for giving him the joy of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170235:23"/>ſalvation; for he was ſo ſatisfied concerning the favour and mercy of God towads him in Jeſus Chriſt, that he rather now deſired death then feared it: as ſeeing death through Jeſus Chriſt without a ſting.</p>
            <p>On the Lords Day towards evening the Lord Mayor (to whoſe Conference I refer you) went the third and laſt time to viſit him (for the next day he was to die) and my Lords advice very much refreſhed his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it being his Lordſhips deſign to ſpeak of Heaven, with the glory and joy of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to eſtabliſh the Priſoners thoughts thereon.</p>
            <p>After his Lordſhip had left him, he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be very chearful in his ſpirit, bleſſing God, that he ſhould put it into his Lordſhips heart to condeſcend ſo far as to pray, and confer with ſuch a deſpicable poor wretch as he was, heartily thanking his Lordſhip for his abundant love.</p>
            <p>That night being his laſt night, I kept him company in Newgate, ſo did divers others; continuing with him in the Dungeon, or Hole (for ſo the Keepers call it) till towards midnight, conferring with him, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to comfort him to the end; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted all the time of his Impriſonment, in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170235:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtian Company, and ſpiritual Diſcourſes; but in his laſt night he was very much carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth to ſpend himſelf about ſpiritual things: So that we judged it meet to leave him alone a while, leſt being altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſt and refreſhment in his body, he might thereby be made unfit for the ſervice of the next day, intending then to declare what the Lord had done for him, and to ſpeak alſo by way of Counſel to thoſe that came to ſee his execution.</p>
            <p>When we had withdrawn for two or three hours from him into the Lodge, (ſome of us obſerving in the mean time that he did ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and as we ſuppoſed that he ſlept alſo) then we all returned to him, he lying cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Bed in his cloaths; when we came again about him, he raiſed up himſelf, and fell afreſh to his former good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Then I ſat down by him, and did read the 14 verſe of the 51 Pſalm, <hi>Deliver me from blood-guiltineſs O God, thou God of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſs.</hi> I then divided the Verſe into theſe two parts:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Davids</hi> prayer, <hi>Deliver me from blood-guiltineſs, O God,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Davids</hi> promiſe and engagement to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170235:24"/>God upon the granting of his deſire, <hi>And my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Then I made theſe Obſervations from the words of <hi>David,</hi> Viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Obſ.</hi> Not only a wicked unregenerate man, but a gracious godly man may (poſſibly) commit a moſt horrid murther. <hi>David</hi> was <hi>blood-guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Obſ.</hi> The ſin of Murther is a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſin where-ever it is found: <hi>Deliver;</hi> [now that word implyeth danger, <hi>Deliver me,</hi>] if <hi>David</hi> murther, he is in danger of damnation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. Prayer is a work for a perſon guilty of blood; <hi>Deliver me;</hi> this <hi>David</hi> ſaid by way of deſire and ſupplication, yea moſt of this Pſalm ſets forth <hi>Davids</hi> prayer which was preferred upon the account of his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Prayer is the beſt way to obtain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from blood-guiltineſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Obſ.</hi> From thoſe words, <hi>(O God, thou God of my ſalvation)</hi> that, There is ſalvation in God for men that have ſhed blood, if thoſe men become penitent and beg that ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>This Note did refreſh <hi>Nathaniel</hi> very much.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Obſ.</hi> From the Promiſe. <hi>And my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſs,</hi> that men who know what it is to have the guilt of ſin
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170235:24"/>(guilt of blood or any other ſin) taken away, will certainly ſing aloud of Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, faithfulneſs, truth.</p>
            <p>And indeed this poor man did magnifie God and ſing aloud of his righteouſneſs, making mention of his, and his only; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired us to ſing Pſalms ſeveral times with him, and to rejoyce with him, which alſo we did.</p>
            <p>About five a clock he fell into ſuch a rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and extaſie of conſolation as I never ſaw, nor (I beleeve) any of my fellow-Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators; for he would ſhout for joy that the Lord ſhould look on ſuch a poor vile crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as he was: He often cried out, and made a noiſe, and indeed did not know how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and ſignifie fully enough his inward ſenſe of Gods favour, ſaying, <hi>Muſt he be an heir, an heir of God, and a joynt-heir with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, a fellow Citizen with the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> He could not bear ſuch a glorious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. Now that his joy was right Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical joy, appeareth thus, in that mourning and bitterneſs went before it; yea, he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with trembling, and could exceedingly often ſay that he would yet have a deeper, and a more thorow ſenſe of ſin; he could never be ſufficiently abaſed before the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170235:25"/>
            <p>Now the time was at hand that he ſhould be carried forth to Execution, but he thought it was not neer enough; for he asked ſeveral times, What a clock is it? I demanded why he enquired ſo concerning the time of the day? Would you gladly die? ſaid I. Yes, yes, ſaith he, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt which is beſt of all.</hi> About ſeven the Coach came to carry him away; the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per knockt off his Irons, and now he was a freeman indeed; for the hand of Grace had before this time taken away the Fetters and Bolts about his Spirit and Conſcience. I went with him in the Coach, and by the way his great deſire was as he paſſed through the Streets to fix his heart more fully on God, and to think with more intention and firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of minde upon the riches, the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able riches of Grace. In a ſhort time ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſſed through many thouſands of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, many of whom prayer for his ſoul, and ſhewed compaſſion otherwiſe to him; he came under the Gibbet which ſtood in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> juſt over againſt the end of <hi>Milk-ſtreet,</hi> where he had done the murder, he went up the Ladder, the Executioner ſtanding above him, and I below upon the Ladder: When he was tied to the Gibbet, he began to ſpeak to the people, having a Speech writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170235:25"/>which he purpoſed to have read through; A true Copie whereof followeth <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Beloved Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Am here a miſerable Creature, and had not God of his infinite Grace and Mercy looked upon me, as ſad a ſpectacle of miſery as ever your eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, by reaſon of my wicked and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful life. And now by the juſtly hand of God I am come here to die juſtly for my ſins: And it is my deſire that all that ſee me, or that hear of me, might learn this moſt true Leſſon from me, that have not learned it from the Word of God in the Scriptures, <hi>That the wages of ſin is death.</hi> I have been a very great ſinner, and as I think, the greateſt of ſinners: And my deſires are that my repentance may be greater then my ſins; Which I am affraid is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be without the infinite mercy of God, who hath graciouſly promiſed to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170235:26"/>accept the will for the deed. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of my ſinful life, I have, for all thoſe who ſhall be pleaſed to look into it, gathered together, and given to my Lord Mayors Chaplain, and intreated him to have it printed for a timely warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all other young-men, eſpecially to the Apprentices of this City, that by my harms, they may through the Grace of God learn to beware.</p>
                     <p>Good people, That which I ſhall ſpeak unto you is but little, becauſe my ſtrength is now but weak: Indeed I wiſh I had more ſtrength, that my words might reach not onely unto the ears, but unto the hearts of every rebellious and diſobedient Child and Servant in this great City, yea, throughout the whole Nation: And my counſel is, that every one would take heed of the beginnings of ſin. I remember when I firſt was enticed unto evil ways and practices, I was tender and fearful of them, and trembled to think what thoſe waies might bring upon me; but I neither
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170235:26"/>hearkened to the Word of God, nor the voice of mine own Conſcience, which exceedingly checked me, but reſolved to go on therein, and through the Devils enticements joyning with my wicked heart, by degrees I grew more bold and hardy in evil waies, every day more then other, and at laſt came to be ſo far har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened in ſin and wickedneſs, that evil waies and actions were as familiar unto me as eating and drinking was.</p>
                     <p>Truly Sirs, This is very true, and this I ſpeak by ſad experience, to warn every one that they would hearken either to Gods Word, or unto their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, when they are firſt checked for their ſins: Therefore good people, as you love your own Souls, take heed of the beginnings of ſin, and kill ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before it grow too ſtrong for you. If I had done ſo, I verily beleeve, and think that ſin had not at this time thus killed me, as now it will certainly do. But ſeeing it is ſo, that I am here brought a poor diſtreſſed Captive unto my death
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170235:27"/>by the Tyranny and cruelty of ſin; it is my deſire that I may through the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſiſtance of God be enabled to do a greater miſchief unto ſin by my death, then ſin hath done unto me in bringing me to this death, which will I hope but kill my body onely, although it be a bitter, curſed and a ſhameful death: Oh hearken to what I have ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and let me for that purpoſe humbly beg of all that either hear me or ſhall hear of me; and oh that I could prevail with every young perſon, to caſt away ſin betimes, to check it in the firſt beginning. I do ſeriouſly think there is no ſuch courſe to deſtroy the growing of it in the hearts of men and women as that would be.</p>
                     <p>Sirs, I am now a dying man, and truly if I knew of any better way to ruine ſin then other in mine own obſervation. I would ſurely now tell you. For I bleſs God I can ſay it truly, that I am a real enemie to ſin, becauſe ſin I find is ſuch a great enemy to God, to all Mankind,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170235:27"/>and particularly, I have found it my greateſt enemy that ever I had. Oh that I had taken this counſel, which now through the great goodneſs and grace of God I have given to you; certainly it would have prevented the growth of ſin in this poor, ſad, and now ſorrowful ſoul of mine: Certainly, I had not now been here as I am, to ſuffer this curſed and ſhameful death which I am juſtly to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer both from God and Man for my moſt foul, horrid, and bloody ſin.</p>
                     <p>The taking away the life of him who was unto me as dear as my Brother; which ſin, I hope God for his Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, hath in mercie to my poor Soul forgiven. This ſin this bloody ſin, I hope the onely wiſe, merciful, gracious and good God hath ſanctified for the everlaſting good of my poor Soul. He who is able to bring light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and good from the greateſt evill, can by his infinite goodneſs bring from this ſin of mine, which is the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Body, the eternal ſalvation of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170235:28"/>my Soul. This is a Mercy never to be forgotten by my friends; that although I have been ſo unhappie as to ſtain their Names and Reputations here, yet I hope through the grace, mercy, and goodneſs of God I may be their joy and rejoycing hereafter. Oh this ſin that the Devil was ſuffered to tempt me to commit, my wicked heart conſenting thereunto! I have obſerved ſince my impriſonment, this blood-guilty ſin, was as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my other ſins which I went on in without conſidering whither I was going. Had I truly and timely repented of my former ſins, I verily beleeve and am fully perſwaded I had prevented this; this foul, this horrid ſin, for which I can never be too much affected nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. Yet nevertheleſs, this ſin I hope through the grace of God hath been a rouſing, and an awakening ſin to me; it hath cauſed me to call to remembrance all my former ſins, and to be humbled for them, and I hope through the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aſſiſtance of God I have truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170235:28"/>of them all. I thank God for his mercy, I can truly ſay, that I am now another manner of Creature then formerly I was: Formerly God came not into my thought with any joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; but now to think of God is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing precious to my ſoul: To think of the name of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt is the chief joy and rejoycing of my ſoul. This is ſome change, and I think a great change, and I hope a good change; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly I ſinned with great delight, and now through the grace of God I delight not in any ſin; nay, I can truly ſay more, I do now through Gods grace hate and loath ſin; and this I know to be true; for I do even hate my moſt beloved ſin, The ſin of Uncleanneſs, which I do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe all Young-men to watch and pray againſt; and for the more effectual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention thereof to live very temperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſoberly, making no proviſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts thereof. This ſin, I bleſs God for his grace, I can now truly ſay I hate it, I hope if I were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170235:29"/>to live as many years in the world as I may do moments, I ſhould through the grace of God never commit more: And the ſin of Lying which formerly I made no conſcience of, I think I can truly ſay now through the grace of God thar I truly hate it as a wicked ſin, and Lying now is ſo baſe an evil in my ſight that <hi>I</hi> could not be hired to tell a lye, no not <hi>I</hi> hope if <hi>I</hi> had the promiſe of my life givenme, which in my condition is the greateſt gift which man can beſtow upon me; yet <hi>I</hi> hope, even for my life, to ſave it from this terrible death, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not be tempted to ſin againſt ſo good a God, who hath given me the hopes of an eternal life, and delivered me from a thouſand times a more terrible death; nor againſt my bleſſed Redeemer, who died to take away my ſins and who hath thus graciouſly looked upon me, ſo vile, ſo wicked, and ſo miſerable a ſinner as <hi>I</hi> have been; and hath ſhewed mercy upon me, not for any worth that is in me, who am the unworthieſt of all men, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170235:29"/>for his own names ſake, becauſe mercy pleaſeth him: To whom therefore be glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have now declared unto you the grounds I have of my hope, that I have made my peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt, and have obtained through his grace and mercy my perfect reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God, and my bleſſed Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt. I ſhall in the next place in deep humility, as being very ſenſible that I have wronged very many, and therefore I do here humbly beg my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from all the World, for all the wrong and injury that I have in any kind done unto any one: And indeed I ſhould be glad, if I could, to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to every one: but that I am not able to do; and therefore I muſt content my ſelf with begging their pardon and forgiveneſs, which I do here deſire from every one, man, woman and child, even for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, whom it is that they themſe ves muſt all fle unto for his pardon, or elſe be miſerable for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170235:30"/>ever; and as they deſire the Lord Jeſus ſhould forgive them all their wrongs done againſt him, ſo I hope they will for his ſake forgive me all mine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt them. And as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired my pardon and forgiveneſs from all the world for the wrongs and injuries which I have done; ſo I do here deſire to declare, and that freely and with all my ſoul, that I do truly forgive all the World for all the wrongs that I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from every one therein, even thoſe evil Companions of mine which have in any kind been the Devils inſtruments in tempting me, and thereby have brought me unto that evil which here I am now to undergo, even the loſing of my life: Confeſſing it was more mine own evil and ſin in conſenting to do thoſe wicked actions which have occaſioned me now to be here to ſuffer, then theirs; and I am more to blame my ſelf in being here, then any other whatſoever. I am fully ſatisfied, that through Gods aſſiſtance I might have reſiſted the temptation, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170235:30"/>avoided that evil I have done; ſo that that the true cauſe of this my preſent miſery is wholly mine own; though I intend not hereby to excuſe the Devil nor any of his Inſtruments. I therefore here once more adviſe all young men and women to take heed of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of evil, and to take heed that they never forſake God, nor his ways and counſels; for I have found that there firſt began my ruine, neglecting Gods Word, and not regarding his counſels given me there, he left me to mine own ways and unto mine own counſels, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, as a juſt puniſhment for my great wickedneſs in leaving God, and the directions which he had given me for my good. And as I deſire to forgive every one, ſo it is my heary prayer, that God for Chriſts ſake will forgive them for all that is evil in any of them. And let me ſay this to magnifie the infinite goodneſs of God, who oft-times makes a poor Creatures extremity to be his own opportunity: I might now have been
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170235:31"/>going from this place to Hell, had not the mercy of God prevented me, which I hope he hath done for his own names ſake, and for his dear Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, who is my bleſſed Redeemer, who hath purchaſed life and ſalvation for all humble, penitent, and believing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of whom I hope I am one, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire to manifeſt the truth of my Faith by all the means which God hath enabled me; and where I am not able to do what I would, Phope God in mercy will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the will for the deed.</p>
                     <p>I have now almoſt done: As I have been a wondrous greaſt ſinner, and God hath ſhewed forth wondrous mercy to ſave me; ſo it hath pleaſed God to ſhew forth wonderful kindneſs to me, in ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and moving my <hi>Lord Major</hi> to move the Bench to give me ſo large a time of Repentance; and not only ſo, but his Lordſhip hath uſed great means not only in ſending me the aſsiſtance of good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but he alſo came twice himſelf to viſit me, and prayed with me; which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170235:31"/>kindneſs of his I pray God to reward a hundred ſold into his boſom. And here I deſire to bleſs God as for the time and means for repentance, ſo for the grace and heart to repent which all were effects of the wonderful love of God towards me ſo vile and wicked a ſinner as I have been.</p>
                     <p>I have great reaſon alſo in all humili y to thank the good people of this City for their many prayers to God for me, and for their kind viſits of me: I hope they will believe that God hath heard their prayers on my behalf, and wil viſit them, even every one of them that in love to my poor ſoul have viſited me in this my great neceſsity. And it is my deſire and hope, that the good people of this City may by this experiment be ſo encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as never to ceaſe ſeeking of God for his grace for any ſinner whatſoever, who of his infinite grace and mercy hath had reſpect unto ſo wicked, ſo vile and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Creature as I was, out of whom <hi>I</hi> hope <hi>I</hi> may truly ſay, he hath caſt forth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170235:32"/>legions of ſins, and left in me none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind to hinder my acceſs unto God by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> have now done: What ſhall <hi>I</hi> ſay more? Lord teach me what to ſay, that <hi>I</hi> may glorifie thee, who haſt thus glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the riches of thy mercy upon me, a poor vile Creature; as a cloſe of what <hi>I</hi> have to ſay, and ſo therewith to cloſe up my life, my wicked and ſinful life, and withall go into a life where I ſhall ſin no more, offend God no more, but be in an eſtate of bleſſing and praiſing God for ever and ever. And therefore unto that God of all grace, who is able to keep that which <hi>I</hi> ſhall commit unto his truſt, and to preſerve me both ſould and body; into thy hands, O merciful Father and bleſſed Redeemer, <hi>I</hi> commit my ſoul; humbly beſeeching thee to remember that good word whereupon I deſire to reſt and wholly caſt my ſelf, even the ſure word of thy faithfulneſs, O bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our! from whoſe ſweet lips dtopped this ſweet ſaying, <hi>That whoſoever cometh
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170235:32"/>unto him, he will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> This bleſſed ſaying hath been, and at preſent is the joy and comfort of my ſoul. And for this body of mine, which hath been a body of ſin, it is now through grace become the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt. And as the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> believed, and therefore he ſpake; ſo <hi>I</hi> believe, and therefore ſpeak; That he that raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe me up alſo by Jeſus, and preſent me unto God without blame.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> have done. Good people, all you that have had the patience to bear me thus long, let me humbly beg your prayers with me, and for me, That he which hath begun a good work in me, will finiſh it until the day of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Nathaniel Butler</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170235:33"/>
            <p>After he had read ſome part of this Speech, the people preſſing and making a noiſe, I told Mr. Sheriff <hi>Milner,</hi> that I humbly conceived it beſt for the Malefactor to forbear reading any further, the people not being able to hear becauſe of the noiſe, and that he ſhould rather ſpeak briefly from his own breaſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out book; whereunto Mr. Sheriff conſented, and the Priſoner put up his written Speech, and ſpake then with a very loud voice, and with abundance of tears, to this effect:</p>
            <p>That he would humbly deſire the Magiſtrates of <hi>London</hi> to look after the ſuppreſſion of Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites; for ſome of the Popiſh party had been with him in priſon, perſwading him (but in vain) to die in the Roman Catholique Religion. Then he addreſſed himſelf to Maſters and Servants, adviſing and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them ſtrongly to be both very watchful and careful in their ſeveral ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities; Maſters to look well after their Servants, and Servants to ſerve their Maſters in ſingleneſs of heart; admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and exhorting all men to fear the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170235:33"/>Lord, ſaying, <hi>If you love your ſouls, leave off evil ways, and be warned by mine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: But if ye will keep your ſins, and hope for pardon, God will keep his pardon, and you ſhall keep your ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having finiſhed his Speech, he then called on the Lord by Prayer, intreating the people to join with him: He prayed with an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated voice, and with many tears, this Prayer following.</p>
            <q>
               <p>O <hi>Merciful GOD! which according to the multitude of thy mercies doeſt ſo put away the ſins of thoſe which truly repent, that thou remembrest them no mnore:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Open thine Eye of Mercy upon me wretched Sinner that I am! who moſt earneſtly deſire pardon and forgiveneſs of all my former ſins, and particularly for my late horrid Blood guiltineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, if it be not too late (and I truſt no time is too late for thee to ſhew mercy) waſh away this blood of my Brother, which ſticks ſo cloſe to my ſoul, in the blood of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170235:34"/>my Saviour (O let me call him ſo!) which was ſhed for my ſins, and the ſins of the whole world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let not the voice of my murdered Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood cry louder for vengeance, then the blood of our crucified Jeſus be heard to cry for pardon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give me, Lord, a truly penitent heart; and then accept of that penitent heart of mine, which is thine own gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Given me, plenty of briniſh tears; but firſt ſteep and waſh thoſe tears of mine in the wounds of thy Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Make me here to abhor, and loath, and judge, and condemn my ſelf; that in thy great day hereafter, The great day of the Lord, I may not be condemned eternally both body and ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Renew in me, most loving Father, whatſoever hath been decayed by the fraud and malice of the Devil, or by mine own bloody carnal will and frailneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſe me to ſet all my ſins before my face, and then do thou cast them behind thy back.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170235:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſe me to ſpread all my ſins before thee my God, as</hi> Hezekiah <hi>did the the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Papers of</hi> Rabſhekah; <hi>and then do thou blow them away with the blast of thy holy Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And foraſmuch as I do humbly and earneſtly deſire to put my trust only in thy mercy, Impute not unto me my former or latter ſins; the ſins of my body, and the ſins of my ſoul; ſins of omiſsion, or ſins of commiſsion; ſins which I have done to pleaſe my ſelf, or others; ſins againſt the Firſt, or against the Second Table; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee my God, againſt my Neighbor, or againſt mine own Sonb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let this firſt death of mine, which I am now ready to pay in ſatisfaction to Man's Law, be acceptable in thy ſight, O God; and ſo do thou deliver me from the ſecond death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deliver me from my Blood guiltineſs O God, and take me yet into thy favour, through the merits and blood ſhedding of thy moſt dearly beloved Son, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amen! Amen!</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170235:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from my blood guiltineſs! who ſhall deliver me from this body of ſin and death!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord have mercy upon me a ſinner!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt have mercy upon me a ſinner!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord have mercy upon me a ſinner; A Mercileſs, a Profane, a Thieving, a Bloody ſinner!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, though I had no mercy upon my Brother, yet do Thou have mercy upon me: For, Lord, I have ſo much the more need of mercy for my ſoul, by how much I had ſo little mercy upon his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, I confeſs with horror of ſoul, that I killed him ſuddenly, giving him no time to prepare for death:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet, Lord, I muſt confeſs to thy great glory and goodneſs, that Thou haſt given me time and reſpite to repent before I die.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170235:35"/>
            <p>He then deſir'd me, as I ſtood upon the Ladder, to pray for him; which I alſo did, he joining therein very ſolemnly. I then having done prayer, asked him how he did? He told me, he doubted not of doing well; he laid all behind him, and would go to Chriſt alone for life and ſalvation; ſaying, <hi>Now I am lanching into the Ocean of Eternity!</hi> Then he delivered to me the written Speech, deſiring the Executioner to forbear Turning him off, till he lifted up his hands and ſaid, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſoul!</hi> I then took him by the hands, and took my leave of him. After he had ſtood ſtill a little while in a way of Ejaculations, with his Cap over his eyes; he lifted up his hands, and ſaid the words aforeſaid: Then the Executioner did his office, and he was a dead man in a few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And in a few moments more, who knows which of us will not be dead men alſo? Oh conſider therefore, all you that yet are alive, the following Admonition.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170235:36"/>
            <head>An Admonition to all perſons whatſoever, eſpecially to Parents, and Children; Maſters, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO Parents and Maſters of Families; hear what the Lord faith to you, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is a putting of a thing into the mind, an urging and preſſing of it, an informing and inſtructing the mind. <hi>Leigh. crit ſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Now this Text tells you of two very great faults, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, In caſe admoniſhing of Children and Servants be totally omitted; where's then your obedience to God, who leaves their Education to your care? Nay, inſtead of giving good advice and examples to Youth, you many times (I mean many Heads of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies) rather ruine them, by living without Knowledge and without Conſcience your ſelves. Oh conſider this, and acquaint your ſelves with God and with Jeſus Chriſt, that you may be able to acquaint all committed to your nurture with the fame God and with the ſame Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the knowing of whom is the excellencie of knowledge.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170235:36"/>
            <p>Secondly, A word to men of care (but of very little care) in this thing: I grant you uſe prayer, and you read Sermon-notes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and the Scriptures themſelves among your people at home; but how often? and how earneſtly is that exerciſe? Alas, once it may be on the Lords day, and then no great regard had how they profit, or whether they profit or no, ſo that ſomething be done, though nothing come by it by way of benefit to their Souls. 'Tis a wonderful weakneſs in many great Profeſſors of Religion, who will pray and beg of God ſtrongly upon their knees for Light, Knowledge, Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to be given to their dear Children, and to their Servants; and yet theſe very perſons will contribute little or nothing beſides good wiſhes towards the converſion and welfare of ſouls, that (by their importunate ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations) ſeem to be precious in their eye. If praying be all you have to do for your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, what mean then thoſe many Scriptures that command the doing of many other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties beſides praying with, and praying for your people? and if prayer onely be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, why do you onely pray? Indeed 'tis well done, to wiſh well to them that dwell with you (though it be part) it is the leaſt part of your duty; doth not the Lord look
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170235:37"/>for much more from you? doth he not charge Fathers, and Mothers, and Maſters to inſtruct, rebuke, correct their Children and Servants, and to call them to account concerning their profiting in Goſpel knowledge? I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the careleſneſs of you in theſe things is that which renders Preaching ſo unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. What will it profit you, or yours, to hear Sermons, and after that never to hear more of them? Take heed of ignorance and idleneſs; ignorance, in not knowing what ye ought to do; and idleneſs in refuſing to take pains with your people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. Formerly, <hi>They that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkened and heard, and a book of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance was written before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought on his name.</hi> But now how ſeldom do we ſee Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies conferring among themſelves, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife ſpeaking of God and of Chriſt, that Children may learn. Where is a Maſter and Miſtris, or Maſter and Dame that now adaies drop one gracious word in the hearing of their Servants the whole week or moneth, nay (it may be) the whole year throughout? is it any wonder then for young ones and inferiors to fall into evil ways, when you that are elder, and their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170235:37"/>Tutors and Governors, walk ſo looſely and unchriſtianly before them? Will you now ſearch the Scriptures, and know your work, and do it entirely? will you be faithful and true to all thoſe Souls the Lord hath entruſted you with? and take heed leaſt their preſent miſcarriages, and their after-condemnation be (and it will be, unleſs you do all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to your part) charged upon your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> hath given me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand, that if he had continued with one Maſter to whom he was turned over, he beleeved he never had come to ſuch a paſs as he did. The day is coming, when it will come to paſs that God ſhall ſet your ſins and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults in order before your faces. And dare you then accuſe God, or can you excuſe your ſelves, when in truth it ſhall be laid to your charge, that ſuch a Son, ſuch a Daughter, ſuch a Man-ſervant, or Maid-ſervant had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done ſo wickedly in one kind or other, they never had faller into the waies of the Devil, nor fallen under the wrath of God, if we who had the nurturing, over-ſight, and admoniſhing of them, had done our duty.</p>
            <p>O remember the counſel of Chriſt in theſe two, Scriptures; That of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> 5.4. and latter end lately touched upon,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170235:38"/>
               <hi>Bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord:</hi> That is, teach them to know, and love, to ſerve and fear the Lord; give them ſuch nurture and inſtruction, ſuch ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual matter for their minds to work upon, as the Lord preſcribeth by the Scriptures. The other Text of very great uſe and ſervice to Maſters, is in <hi>Col.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Maſters, give to your Servants that which is juſt and equal, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that alſo ye have a Maſter in Heaven.</hi> 'Tis not onely juſt and equal to give food and raiment, or knowledge or underſtanding in a Trade, to your Servants; but 'tis juſt and equal for you to give good counſel to your Servants to ſerve God; and till this be, you are unjuſt men, and unequal in your waies, unconſcionable as to the ſouls of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>'Tis a very honourable character that the moſt High himſelf gives to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.19 <hi>For I know him, that he will command his Children and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord— Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did not command his Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to honour him, and ſerve him onely, (for ſo moſt men are apt enough to lay their commands upon children and houſholds) but his command required his Relations to walk in the way of God. If men would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170235:38"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> herein, what orderly, holy and reformed Families would then be found in the Land? I hope that theſe Scripture-paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and paſſages of providence alſo (one whereof, and indeed a very ſad one, you have ſeen in the fore-going Narrative) will touch your hearts, and engage you to look after this, that you and your Children, you and your Servants be henceforth found in the way of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Many Maſters are very like the Egyptian Task-maſters in two reſpects, which are both remarkable, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Egyptians made the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to ſerve with rigor, and they made their lives bitter with hard bondage in Morter and in Brick, and in all manner of ſervice in the field; all their ſervice wherewith they made themſerve was with rigor,</hi> Exod. 1.13, 14. O the rigor and bitterneſs that ſome ſervants abide during the time of their ſerving ſome men! how many mercileſs, harſh, cruel Parents and Maſters are more like <hi>Egyptians</hi> then <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> more like Turks then Chriſtians by their cruelty, provoking (directly againſt the Goſpel-Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute) Sons, Daughters, and Servants to do that which without unreaſonable provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they would never have done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Too many Heads and Rulers of houſes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170235:39"/>ſeem Egyptians rather then Chriſtians, not only in exacting ſervice from their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours with all ſtormineſs and bitterneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but likewiſe in this ſenſe (more wicked then the former) that they will not (ſo far are theſe men from preſſing their ſervants to ſerve God) ſuffer them to go and ſerve the Lord; do not ſome upbraid and revile, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and diſcourage Servants, and Sons and Daughters, if they look after goodneſs and exactneſs of life? <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.16. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſay, The Lord God of the Hebrews bath ſent me unto thee ſaying, Let my people go that they may ſerve me in the wilderneſs; and behold, hitherto thou wouldeſt not hear.</hi> I beg of you theſe two things. 1. That you would be content when your children and ſervants do perform to you reaſonable ſervice. And 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> that you would exhort and beſeech <hi>them by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God to preſent their bodies a living ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their reaſonable ſervice.</hi> But leaſt I ſhould not prevail with you, I ſhall therefore direct my counſel and admonition to children and ſervants themſelves that in caſe your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers ſee not their duty, or do it not; yet your ſelves may make conſcience to carry it ſo towards God and all men that ye adorn thereby the Doctrine of God our Saviour.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170235:39"/>
            <p>Young people, hear what Chriſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Children obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right; this is well-pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. Gol.</hi> 3.20. The Lord is angry at, and diſpleaſed with diſobedient Sons and Daughters. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.5.6, 7, 8. <hi>Servants</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> a ſervant of Chriſt) <hi>be obedient to them that are your maſters according to the fleſh,</hi> (for as to ſoul and conſcience Chriſt only is Lord and Maſter and in this ſenſe we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to <hi>call any man Maſter,</hi> Matth. 23 8.) <hi>with fear and trembling, in ſingleneſs of your heart, as unto Chriſt: Not with eye-ſervice as men-pleaſers, but as the ſervants of Chriſt, doing the will of God from the heart; With good will doing ſervice, as to the Lord, and not to men, Knowing that whatſoever good thing any man doth</hi> (though never ſo mean a ſervant) <hi>the ſame ſhall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome ſervant may ſay, My Maſter is a very harſh froward man, or elſe I could willingly ſerve him in ſingleneſs of heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auſ.</hi> Thou art bound by the Goſpel to obey and be in ſubjection to ſuch a man, if he be thy Maſter, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 218, 19. <hi>Servants be ſubject to your Maſters with all fear,</hi> (of neglecting their lawful commands) <hi>not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward. For this is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170235:40"/>thank-worthy, if a man for conſcience toward God endure grief, ſuffering wrongfully. For what glory is it, if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye take it patiently? but if when ye do well, and ſuffer for it, ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God. For even here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye were called; becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us, leaving us an example that you ſhould follow his ſteps; Who did no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth; Who when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he ſuffered, he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly.</hi> I confeſſe it were well for Maſters (for wo to them that are naught and froward, making their ſervants to ſuffer words, and buffetings and other abuſes wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) and well for Servants if they could ſerve men gentle and good; but however, they ſerve a God and Saviour that's good, and that will reward all that ſuffer leſſe or more for his ſake: As my advice to you is that you would honour and obey, and be faithful in all things to your Maſters, ſo I beſeech you ſhun all ſins, and all appearance of evill, but eſpecially flee from idle companions. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20. <hi>He that walks with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe, but a companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deboiſt, drunken, ſwearing, curſing, whoring wretches are fools in the ſenſe of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170235:40"/>Scripture; and ſeeing it is ſelf-deſtructive to be a companion with ſuch perſons, wilt thou walk any more with ſuch? drinking to drunkenneſs, Dicing and Carding are things of evill report, and very evill things; they lead likewiſe to other evils. <hi>Nathaniel But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> was a great Company keeper, and a great Gameſter, and what did he grow to at the laſt? 2. <hi>Flee</hi> (2 Tim. 2.22.) <hi>youthfull luſts. Flee fornication,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. But before a man will flee from any thing, he muſt ſee that thing to be dangerous; Now that Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Uncleanneſs and Whoredom is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, I demonſtrate thus, (whereby it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear every way deſtructive) that it 1. Endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gereth Reputation, 'tis a diſhonour to the name and perſon of a Man or Woman, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.17. <hi>There ſhall be no whore of the daughter of Iſrael, nor a Sodomite of the ſons of Iſrael: Thou ſhalt not bring the hire of a whore, or the price of a dog into the houſe of the Lord thy God for any vow; for even both theſe are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto the Lord thy God.</hi> Rom. 1.24. <hi>Wherefore God gave them up unto uncleanneſs through the luſts of their own hearts, to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their own bodies among themſelves.</hi> Heb. 13.4. <hi>Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed underfiled</hi> (implying the defiled is ſhameful) <hi>but whoremongers and adulterers God will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170235:41"/>judge.</hi> 2. Endangereth ſubſtance, <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.3. <hi>Who ſo loveth wiſdom rejoyceth his father, but he that keepeth company with harlots, ſpendeth his ſubſtance.</hi> How many have ſpent fair Eſtates by following this filthy ſin! Many ſpend their own ſubſtance, and that alſo which is not their own (but their Maſters or Parents) upon impudent wicked whoriſh women; it is a diſgracing and an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhing ſin; who ſees not this by experience oftentimes? 3. Following Harlots will lead thee to Hell, will provoke God to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5, 7, 8, 9. <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this? thy chidren have forſaken me, and ſworn by them that are no gods; when I had fed them to the full then they committed adultery, and aſſembled themſelves by troops in Harlots houſes</hi> (the vengeance of God will rout and miſerably deſtroy ſuch troops, when he ſets himſelf in array againſt them) <hi>they were as fed horſes in the morning, every one neighed after his neighbours wife: Shall I not viſit for theſe things? ſaith the Lord, and ſhall not my ſoul</hi> (wo then to their ſouls) <hi>be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> Prov. 7.25, 26, 27. <hi>Let not thine heart decline to her ways. go not aſtray in her path, for ſhe hath caſt down many wounded</hi> (wounded in their credit, wounded in their Eſtates, and wounded in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170235:41"/>their Conſciences) <hi>yea many ſtrong men have been ſlain by her.</hi> This is a bloody, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſlaying ſin. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Her houſe is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To live in chambering and wantonneſs is the way to lie down in the chambers of death. Remember the two young men named in the Narrative, who were lately bedfellows above ground, and now are become chamber-fellows bellow; for the fear of the Lord prolongeth dayes, but the years of the wicked ſhall be ſhortned; break off then ſpeedily from all ſin, as you hope for long-laſting life here, and for everlaſting life hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> We can repent, and mourn, and pray hereafter: For did not <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> live a long time wickedly, and repented in a ſhort time at the laſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Do not think that you can repent when you pleaſe; if you put off Repentance, you put it to a peradventure, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.25. <hi>In meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if God peradventure will give them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to the acknowledging of the truth.</hi> Do as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.20. who made <hi>haſte and delayed not to keep the Commandments of God</hi> Delays in matters relating to life are moſt dangerous. I hope no man nor woman will preſume that the Lord is any way obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170235:42"/>to wait upon them ſo long as they pleaſe; indeed it pleaſeth him to wait to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, but who knows how neer to a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod the time of Gods attendance on ſinners is? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>And the times of this ignorance God winked at, but now commandeth alt men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where to repent.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe (as ſome men count ſlackneſs) but is long ſuffering to us ward not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all</hi> (as <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>men every where</hi>) <hi>ſhould come to repentance.</hi> The Goſpel of God, and the goodneſs of God are gone forth for this very end, to lead men to repentance; but if ſinners refuſe to repent, <hi>then after their hardneſs, and impenitent heart</hi> (under the Goſpel, goodneſs, and long-ſuffering of God) <hi>they treaſure to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> Rom. 2.5. 1. God hath a day of grace for every poor ſinner; 2. He hath a day of wrath for men finally impenitent. Think on it; is it not a thing proper and likely to provoke God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you <hi>to ſwear in his wrath, you ſhall never enter into his reſt,</hi> ſeeing men deſpiſe his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and do <hi>receive his grace in vain?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170235:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Nathaniel Batler</hi> being Executed in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> over againſt <hi>Milk-ſtreet</hi> End, about eight or nine in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (a Multitude of People being Spectators) he was afterwards cut down, and his Corps put into that Coach which brought him to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and from thence conveyed to <hi>Gregories</hi> Churchyard <hi>London;</hi> where about Noon he was burled. That Evening at <hi>S. Gregordes</hi> Church, a Sermon was preached by Mr <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph Yearwood</hi> the Lord Majors Chaplain; (there being a great conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of People,) The Subſtance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, take as followeth:</head>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170235:43"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>I JOH. 3.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Whoſoever hateth his Brother is a Murderer, and ye know that no Murderer hath eternal Life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtles intent in this Epiſtle was (and indeed my deſign in this Sermon is) to promote true love in mens hearts towards one another: His Arguments are many, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth as ſo many provocations to love. Conſider theſe ſeven.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Arg.</hi> 1 John 5.9, 10, 11. <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkneſs, even until now. He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him. But he that hateth his brother, is in darkneſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whether he goeth, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded his eyes</hi> (as though he ſhould ſay) Love ſurpaſſeth hatred, as far as light excelleth darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Men are not of God, but they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170235:43"/>are the children of the Devil, unleſs they love as brethren. This is plain and manifeſt, 1 John 3.10. <hi>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that loveth not his brother,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.7. <hi>Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God: and every one that loveth, is born of God—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>He that Ioveth not, knoweth not God, for God is love,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. A man otherwiſe cannot clear up his love to God, 1 Joh. 4.20. <hi>If a man ſay, I love God and hateth his Brother, he is a Lyar. For he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. 1 John. 4.10.11. <hi>Herein is love, not that we loved God: but that he loved us, and ſent his Son to be the propitiation for our ſins. Beloved, if God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. If you love the Brethren, ye have paſſed from death to life, 1 Joh. 3.14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. The laſt Argument is drawn from the dreadful eſtate of a man that loves not his brother, 1 Joh. 3.14. <hi>He abideth in death, he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170235:44"/>is a murderer, he hath not eternal life abiding in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I am returned to the words which I intend to handle.</p>
            <q>Whoſoever hateth his Brother is a murderer; and ye know that no murderer hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life abiding in him.</q>
            <p>Here we have two things very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A deſcription of a Goſpel-murderer (for in the ſenſe of our Law, meer hatred doth not make a murderer) <hi>Whoſoever hateth his Brother is</hi> (what is he?) <hi>a Murderer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 A declaration of the damnable ſtate of ſuch a murderer. <hi>And ye know</hi> ('tis a known caſe) <hi>that no murderer hath eternal life abide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Let us conſider the firſt of theſe two truths, in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 1. Whoſoever hateth his Brother is Murderer.</p>
            <p>It is requiſite to ſay ſomething by way of Explication to this truth, and then by way of Application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoever]</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>every one</hi>) every ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious man without exception, whether he be reputed good or bad, holy or unholy, if
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170235:44"/>he hateth his brother he is a murderer; if he be rich or poor, high or low, Magiſtrate or Miniſter, whoſoever he be, if he hate, he is here included in the indictment of murder. <hi>[Whoſoever]</hi> is a term of univerſality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hateth]</hi> By hating two things are hinted in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A comparative reſpect. This firſt is plain in <hi>Gen.</hi> 29: 30. <hi>And he went in alſo unto Rachel, and he loved alſo Rachel more then Leah</hi> — 31. <hi>And when the Lord ſaw that Leah was hated,</hi> — that is, was loved leſs then <hi>Rachel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luk. 14.26. <hi>If any man come to me, and hate not his Father, and Mother, and Wife, and Children, and Brethren, and Sisters; yea, and his own life alſo, cannot be my Diſciple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now 'tis not lawful properly and indeed to hate a mans ſelf or his Relations, though he might gain heaven thereby. Obſerve, <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangeliſt ſaith, cap. 14.26. If a man hate not — brethren — he cannot be Chriſts Diſciple; and <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>Whoſoever hateth his brother is a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer</hi> — So that we muſt take the term <hi>[hate]</hi> in ſome places to ſignifie a leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of love: ſo in <hi>Luke.</hi> He that loveth not Chriſt more then himſelf, more then his Wife or Children, more then Brethren or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170235:45"/>ſiſters cannot be my Diſciple; as ſuppoſe a man muſt either forſake Jeſus Chriſt, or elſe his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and near relation; this for ſaking of them, and cleaving to Chriſt, the Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by hating of them; not that men hate, or may lawfully hate their Friends, but they love them leſs then they love the Lord Chriſt, So <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that loveth Father or Mother more then me, is not worthy of me; and he that loveth Son or Daughter more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Hating is taken for a very ſtrong diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and a mighty implacable diſaffection in the heart of one man towards another mans perſon; inſomuch that a man cannot find in his heart to ſay well of, or do good unto another; but he can find in his heart to ſpeak all manner of evil, and act all manner of miſchief, hurt and wickedneſs againſt another. This is our Apoſtles ſenſe; <hi>He that hateth his brother, i.e.</hi> he that ſheweth no pitty or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to, but prejudice, cruelty, and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt his brother, is a Murderer. This is utter hatred, according to that in <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.2.—<hi>I verily thought thou hadſt utterly hated her.</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Brother]</hi> 1. Natural brother, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.18. <hi>And Jeſus walking by the ſea of Galilee, ſaw two brethren, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170235:45"/>
            <p n="2">2. Kinſman and Country-man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3, 4.</p>
            <p>—<hi>For my brethren and kinſmen according to the fleſh, who are Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A Chriſtian, one obedient to Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.48 49.50. —<hi>Who is my mother? and who are my brethren? And he ſtretched forth his hand towards his Diſciples, and ſaid. Behold my mother, and my brethaen: for whoſoever ſhall do the will of my Father which is in heaven, the ſame is my brother.</hi> Heb. 3.1. <hi>Wherefore holy brethren, partakers of the holy calling</hi>—</p>
            <p n="4">4. Any humane creature, man, woman or child, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.3, 4. <hi>And why beholdeſt thou the mote that is in thy brothers eye</hi> (meaning in the eye of any other perſon) <hi>but conſidereſt not the beam that is in thine own eye Or how wilt thou ſay to thy brother</hi> (to any man) <hi>Let me pull out the mote out of thine eye? and behold a beam is in thine own eye!</hi> Acts 17.26. <hi>And hath made of one blood all nations of men for to dwell on all the face of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Is a Murderer]</hi> That is, in his deſire and deſign, and in God's ſenſe and eſteem, who ſearcheth the heart. As a man that doth not commit the act of Adultery, is an Adulterer nevertheleſs if his heart luſt after a woman, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28. So if a man never lay violent hands upon another, yet if his heart diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affect and hate him, he is a Murderer.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170235:46"/>
            <p>[<hi>And ye know that no Murderer</hi> (whether he be a Murderer in the ſenſe of this Scripture, or any other) <hi>hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi>] that is, hath the promiſe of eternal life, or the evidence of it abiding in him. Do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from this clauſe, that a man who was at any time guilty of blood by murthering another, or hating another, cannot be ſaved, or enter into life; for <hi>Manaſſeh, David,</hi> and others were blood-guilty, but upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance were pardoned. I doubt not of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel Butlers</hi> life eternal (though he did deſtroy and take away the life of his Brother) becauſe God gave him repentance and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. The meaning is this; No Murderer hath eternal life abiding in him, if this man abide in his malice, hatred, and under his murder im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent and ſtupid.</p>
            <p>Is he (whoſoever he be) that hateth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, a Murderer? Then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Examine your ſelves. Is Hatred ſo hainous a ſin? How may we know then whether we are not haters of any man? Now Hatred is manifeſted thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By refuſing to rebuke thy brother or neighbor for his ſin. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thine heart; thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy brother, and not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi> Prov. 13.24. <hi>He that spareth the rod, hateth his ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170235:46"/>
            <p n="2">2. By keeping (without cauſe) at a diſtance from men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.27. <hi>And Iſaac ſaid unto them, Wherefore come ye to me, ſeeing ye hate me and have ſent me away from you?</hi> If ye cry, Away with him, away with him, to baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, impriſonment! Away with ſuch an one out of my ſight! I cannot endure this or that perſon in my ſight! Thou art an hater and a murderer. See <hi>Judg</hi> 11.7. <hi>And Jephtah ſaid unto the Elders of Gilead, Did not ye hate me, and expel me out of my fathers houſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Warlike language. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.4. <hi>They hated him, and could not ſpeak peaceably to him.</hi> When men cannot give one another a good word, what is this but malice and hatred in the heart? <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.29. <hi>The archers have ſorely grieved him and ſhot at him, and hated him.</hi> Bending the bow, and ſhooting bitter words, ſpeak out bitterneſs and hatred within.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lying in wait for, riſing up againſt, and mortally wounding another. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.11. <hi>But if any man hate his neighbor, and lie in wait for him, and riſe up againſt him and ſmite him mortally that he die, &amp;c.</hi> Rev. 17.16. <hi>Theſe ſhall hate the whore and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh and burn her with fire.</hi> Harſh uſage ſhews hatred.</p>
            <p>Try your ſelvs by theſe and other Scripture-ſigns, and try impartially.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170235:47"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Exhort men to lay aſide their ſin. See what the word chargeth upon't.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis from the Devill (as love is of God.) 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. Ye are taught of the Devill to hate, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>This is the Meſſage that ye heard from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another, not as</hi> Cain <hi>who was of that WICKED ONE</hi> — meaning as <hi>Cain</hi> was a man of cruelty and hatred, ſo he was of the Divell; hatred is all hatcht in Hell! O then retain it no more in your hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It proves a man to be yet unregenerate, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.2, 3. <hi>For we our ſelves alſo were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fooliſh and diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures, living in MALICE and EN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Y, hatefull and hateing one another. But after that the kindneſs and love of God</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>appeared</hi> &amp;c. Its too too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent from this paſſage that the kindneſs and love of God hath not wrought kindly upon mens hearts ſo long as they live in malice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and hatred; how can a man be a cut throat and a Chriſtian at the ſame time, a man of hatred and a child of God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou art a murderer. I have here tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed ſome ſuteable paſſages of a very reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Godly man (I mean Mr. <hi>Joſeph Caryl</hi>) who in his excellent expoſition upon the 5th Chapter of <hi>Job</hi> and 2 verſe, ſpeaketh thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170235:47"/>wrath. So in like manner wrath is ſaid to ſlay a man; firſt becauſe it thruſts him head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long upon ſuch things as are his death; he runs willfully upon his own death; ſometimes by the dangerouſneſs of the action, when a caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſudden death ſurpriſes him; ſometime by the unlawfulneſs of the action which brings him to a legal judiciary death. Secondly his wrath is ſaid to kill him becauſe his wrath is ſo vexations to him that it makes his life a continual death to him, and at laſt ſo weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him out and waſts his Spirits, that he dies for very grief, and ſo at once commits a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold murder. Firſt, he murders him intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, againſt whom he is wroth. Secondly he really murders his own body. And thirdly he meritoriouſly murders his Soul for ever, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord be more merciful then he hath been wrathful, and the death of Chriſt, heale thoſe wounds by which he would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the death of others, and hath (as much as in him lies) procured his own.</p>
            <p>This is true of hatred as well as of wrath, for he that hateth his brother is a Murderer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He murthers his Brother whom he hates; hatred is a wiſhing and ſeeking for (at leaſt in heart) the ſlaughter, death and deſtruction of his Brother; when the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> affirmeth, whoſoever hateth his Brother is a Murderer;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170235:48"/>his meaning is he is a Murderer of that Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom he hateth, and he is ſo becauſe he hateth him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He that hateth his Brother is a Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more then once; he doth not only murder his brother but himſelf — by bringing etern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al death upon himſelf for hateing his Brother: he that murders himſelf is <hi>(felo de ſe)</hi> a Self-murderer, is manifeſt from theſe words; and ye know that no murderer (meaning a malicious man) hath eternal life abiding in him. To be a murderer is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A crying ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. <hi>And he ſaid, what haſt thou done? the voyce of thy Brothers blood cryeth unto me from the Ground.</hi> If men would think, what am I doing, now I am hateing my Brother; I am murdering in Gods account, and murder is a loud ſin: Surely then we ſhould harbour no hatred. Murder,</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is a very reproachful ſhameful ſin, conſidered in the act that followes it: to prove a man guilty of willfull murder renders him a ſhame to himſelf, a blot to his relations: thou that hateſt, art a murderer! O be aſhamed of this ſhameful ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Murder is a ſin that ſets the vengeance of God againſt a man, the very <hi>Barbarians</hi> beleeve that vengeance and death will fall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170235:48"/>ſtrangely and ſpeedily on Murderers, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4. <hi>And when the</hi> Barbarians <hi>ſaw the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beaſt hang on his hand, they ſaid among themſelves</hi> (very confidently) <hi>no doubt this man</hi> (meaning Paul) <hi>is a murderer, whom though he hath eſcaped the Sea, yet vengeance ſuffereth not to live. Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>But the fearful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving and abominable, and M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERERS,</hi> (heart-murderers and hand-murderers) <hi>and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolaters, and all Liers, ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; which is the Second death.</hi> Tis not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture enough for a Murderer to die only once; God hath deſigned for him a ſecond death, an eternal death; no Murderer (remaining a man of hatred) hath eternall life abiding in him; the Devil himſelf will aſ ſoon be ſaved as he that hateth his Brother. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out are Dogs, ſorcerers, and whoremongers, and murderers</hi> — malicious angells (devills) and malicious men (devils incarnate) muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded together; heaven is no place for men of hatred and malice.</p>
            <p>Three Objections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. But (ſome may ſay) 'Tis no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to hate a poor man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.20. <hi>The poor is hated even of his own e Neighbour; but the rich hath many Friends; no man (nor God</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170235:49"/>himſelf, as ſome men think) mindeth the poor man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. A man ſurely may hate him that ſpeaketh evil, that propheſieth damnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, as in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.8. <hi>And the King of Iſrael ſaid to Jehoſophat, there is yet one man (Macaiah the ſon of Imlah) by whom we may enquire of the Lord, but I hate him, for he doth not propheſie good concerning me, but evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. He hateth me (ſaith another) he is mine enemy; may I not hate him? Matth. 5.43. <hi>Ye have heard that it hath been ſaid, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbor, and hate thine enemy; but I ſay unto you, Love your enemies</hi> — or elſe you will prove your own worſt enemies; for it is death (the ſecond death) to hate a poor man, an enemy, or any man.</p>
            <p>Is hatred a Man-murdering ſin, and a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murdering ſin? Then take heed of helping on this hatred any way. As there are ways to provoke to love (which few love to walk in) ſo there are tricks and devices of the Devil to drive on the deſign of hatred in mens hearts, that he may drive men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Decline (eſpecially) naming men by this or the other name of reproach. D. <hi>Hall,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Norwick,</hi> who was a very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, learned and godly man, in a ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of his, called <hi>Pax terris,</hi> p. 44. ſpeaks thus;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170235:49"/>
               <hi>Damnentur ad imum uſque barathrum illa nominum opprobria, Lutheranorum, Calvinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, Arminianorum, Puritanorum, Praela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum, Presbyterianorum, Independentium, quae fidei ejuſdem profeſſoribus vulgò objectari ſolent. i. e.</hi> Let thoſe terms or names of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and diſgrace (ſaith he) of Lutherans, Calviniſts, Arminians, Puritans, Prelaticals, Presbyterians, Independents, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly objected to the Profeſſors of the ſame faith, let them be condemned to the loweſt hell. I am confident they were coined there, and they prove an occaſion of much helliſh hatred among Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>It's often known that one man hateth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meerly becauſe he paſſeth in the world under one or other of theſe dividing names, whereas (it may be) the man deſerves no ſuch name; but if he do, I am fure it is not fit nor Goſpel-like to leave loving a man of a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent minde in ſome circumſtantial matters of Religion. You will not be able to come off in the day of account by this plea. Indeed I hated ſuch a man, and I thought I did well, for he was called an Epiſcopal man, or a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, or an Arminian, or Anabaptiſt, or a Schiſmatick and Sectary. The Lord God will demand, Was not ſuch a man thy brother, was he not thy neighbour (nay, did he not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170235:50"/>fear my name? notwithſtanding this or that nick-name maliciouſly put on him) and ſhouldſt thou have hated thy Brother, thy Chriſtian Brother, a man that lived in all good conſcience by thee, conſidering this ſtartling Text, <hi>Whoſoever hateth his Brother is a murderer, and ye know</hi> (O then hate no more!) <hi>that no murderer hath eternal life abide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, We ſee the excellency of Love, in 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 12. <hi>ult. — and yet ſhew I unto you a more excellent way.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 'Tis the way of life; as hatred puts mens lives in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and jepoardy; ſo love looks after the ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of life; it permits others to be in peaceable poſſeſſion of their own lives; and then love to brethren is an evidence of that mans life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, that loves his brethren, 1 Joh. 3.14. <hi>We know we have paſſed from death to life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the brethren.</hi> Hatred is deadly and perillons to men every way, and love is of a ſoul-protecting tendency; Love is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and lovely in this reſpect. A <hi>Philanthropie</hi> in us, a love to men, as men; and a love to regenerate men as ſuch, aſſures our hearts we are in the path-way to heaven; as malice and hatred is the high-way to hell, from which the Lord of heaven deliver your ſouls.</p>
            <p>'Tis the way, the high-way to Heaven, a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170235:50"/>man never goes after God till he walks in love, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 5.1, 2: <hi>Be ye therefore followers of God as dear children, and walk in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us.</hi> So long as men (caled Chriſtians) live in bitterneſs, wrath, anger, and clamour, evil ſpeaking, and in malice, they are the Children of the Devil, for him they obey; but when we are kind one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>TENDER-HEARTED,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake is ready to forgive us; this God-like, and Chriſt-like life, this love-life is a lovely evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our following God our heavenly Father, as dear children; and of following our dear Lord and Saviour. Conſider <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 <hi>end.</hi> and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.1, 2. and I hope that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text will make ſmooth, and ſweeten your rough and bitter ſpirits towards each other mutually.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>A Recollection of the ſum of two Diſcourſes between S. T. and <hi>N. B.</hi> in Newgate on Thurſday <hi>Aug. 13.</hi> and Thurſday <hi>Aug. 20, 1657.</hi> both continuing ſeveral houres.</head>
            <p>HAving by the Providence of God upon due occaſion and call, bin with <hi>N. B.</hi> as an eye &amp; Ear witneſs (among others) of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull grace of God to him in his laſt dayes,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170235:51"/>to the rejoycing of my heart; and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and preſt to contribute ſome thing to the Narrative by thoſe worthy perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the publication thereof, I ſhall do it very briefly, according to my beſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and remembrance.</p>
            <p>My firſt addreſs unto him was, to know what ſerious ſenſe he had of his hainous ſin, and his ſoules condition?</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, he did in a very mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner, largely lay open the ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions he had upon his conſcience of the ſinfulneſs and damnableneſs of his ſin, ennu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merating (himſelfe) the ſeveral aggravating circumſtances thereof with the time and manner of his conviction, which began not untill his impriſonment and fetters began. For <hi>albeit</hi> he was followed and filled (as he ſaid) with diſtraction, amazement, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietment, from the time of the fact, making him reſtleſs in all places; Yet he told me he had no ſolid conviction of his ſin, untill he came to be alone in his Chaines, like <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh,</hi> 2 Chron. 33 11.12. his prejudgment of the ſentence of death, brought in the thoughts of an eternall after-eſtate, and then ſaid he, my conſcience was enlightned and a wakened to ſee my ſelf in the glaſs of Gods law, and under the judgment of eternal death,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170235:51"/>which wrought ſuch horror, conſuſion, and aſtoniſhment, that made me cry out in the bitterneſs of my ſoule, as one under the wrath and tertors of the Almighty; Moreover ſaid he, the thoughts of this ſecond and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>death of my poor ſoule, did blot out of my remembrance the death which was approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I began further to apply to him after this manner, That in this your preſent condition, there are two things of greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to your ſoule. Firſt, that you be rightly regulated in your repentance. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, rightly directed the way of beleeving in Chriſt. I ſhall endeavor to make both plain and practicable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not to ſwell the Narrative with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of what I offered him about a true and right conviction of ſin, (not of this notorious ſin only, but of others alſo,) and the corrupt root and fountain from whence all ſprang, with the nature and neceſſity of a Goſpel-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, preſſing ſeriouſneſs and ſincerity upon him, this not being a time to Trifle, much leſs to diſſemble, about the weighty concernments of his ſoule, a falſe and a faigned repentance being as bad as the ſin it ſelf, with more the like, as occaſion was offered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> Anſwers very ſenſibly, in theſe and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170235:52"/>ſuch like words following not in a continued diſcourſe, but in an Intercourſe of ſpeech.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> Oh ſaith he, not only this one hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſin, but multitudes of other ſins, are ſet in order before me, as well ſmall as great; and the ſmalleſt appeareth great to me, as being againſt a holy God and an infinite good; I never thought ſuch things to be ſins, which I now ſee to be ſins. Oh what an ignorant dead Creature was I before! I now apprehend the filthineſs, and feele the hardneſs of my heart; my heart is diſcovered to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome; the whole trade and courſe of my life is brought to my remembrance, (and wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hands the moſt of the time) Oh now ſaith he, I diſcerne I was in a miſerable and damnable condition before I committed this foule fact. Others think themſelves in a happy condition becauſe they are not under the guilt of my ſin, and under the ſame ſentence, but alas they are lamentably miſtaken, as I alſo was. Now do I apprehend the ſinfulneſs of my thoughts and ſecret immaginations, as wel as outward actions: And all this and much more expreſt with ſuch a manner and meaſure of earneſtneſs, as did apparantly ſignifie, that the two-edged Sword had paſt and pierced through the very powers of his ſoule, diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (and abilitating him to diſcerne) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170235:52"/>thoughts and intents of his heart. Oh ſaith he I dare not leſſen my ſins, nor exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate my great ſin, they are againſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous law and holy nature of God; and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in our diſcourſe he would intermix this ſpeech of <hi>Davids,</hi> with hands wringing, and ſtrong affection, <hi>againſt thee O Lord have I ſinned, againſt thee, even thee, O Lord, have I ſinned and done wickedly, and Lord Pardon mine iniquity, for its exceeding great.</hi> Pſal. 25.11. And when I proceeded upon the parts of repentance, and contrition as one great branch of it, he ſaid. That he did heartily repent to his utmoſt as before the Lord; and did hope the Lord would break him more. Oh ſaith he, its the griefe of my heart I can grieve no more, and though my heart is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet I am ſenſible of hardneſs yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (and by way of conceſſion to my words) ſaying, Oh, its not a time to Trifle indeed. I know my heart is deceitfull, but I deſire nothing more then a through and faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the deceitfulneſs of my heart by all that come to mee, that I might not miſtake and loſe my ſoule; and amongſt other deceits I deſire to avoid this of reſting upon any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of mine, but upon Chriſt only for ſalvation: but I hate ſin heartily, not only for that it hath brought mee to this miſery, but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170235:53"/>alſo for its filthy nature; and becauſe againſt a holy and mercifull God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing I endeavoured to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, was, the poſſibility of pardon and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, notwithſtanding the magnitude and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his ſins, which when I began to ſpeake, his heart was raiſed to an earneſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and attention, rejoycing to think there might be a dore of hope I proceeded to three or four conſiderations to evidence his ſin pardonable, and his ſoule ſalvable. Firſt, becauſe there was more grace in God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and more vertue in the blood of Chriſt to ſave, then was in his ſin to damne him. Secondly, becauſe God in the Goſpel had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined all ſins of all ſorts pardonable, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only [the ſin] againſt the holy ſpirit, <hi>Math.</hi> 12.31. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16. which for ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry reaſons he could not poſſibly be guilty of; this I did inculcate the more, that he might ſted faſtly and firmely beleeve the record and teſtimony hereof, before he went further, unto which he did profeſs a full and ſound aſſent, gathering herefrom hopes that he might be ſaved, and exulted in thoſe hopes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that God had recorded eminent examples in his word of ſhewing his mercy, to ſuch ſinners who had committed the ſame ſin,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170235:53"/>and that with a higher hand, <hi>viz.</hi> Manaſſeh. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.16. compared with 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33, 11, 12, 13. I did endeavor to enforce the Parallel, about the meanes and manner of Gods humbling, by the ſame fetters of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; upon which he ſaid, Oh I bleſs God for this affliction, I bleſs God that I was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and taken; I might have run out my courſe in ſin, and directly to hell, had not God taken this courſe with me. Oh I would not exchange my preſent impriſonment with my former liberty in ſin for all the world. I hinted alſo the Murder of <hi>David</hi> in the matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> prayer again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.11. which he ſaid Mr. <hi>Samuel Jacombe</hi> of Lumbard Stret had preacht on in the Priſon, which did much help his hopes, and he voluntarily called to remembrance the Jewes who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36.37.38. and made a comfortable improvement thereof.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I alledged that the Goſpell did pronounce and proclaim pardon of ſin; and eternal ſalvation upon true repentance, and beleeving on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and there was no viſible barr to exclude him more then any other in world: the ſubſtance of this faith lying in this, that if upon the ſight of his loſt condition by ſin, and upon a firme aſſent to the record of God concerning his ſons being
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170235:54"/>an only and al-ſufficient Saviour, he could but caſt himſelf upon the mercy of God, and roule his ſinfull ſincking ſoule upon the Lord Jeſus as a foundation, heartily hateing ſin, and abhorring himſelf, and cleaving to Chriſts righteouſneſs, he ſhould be certainly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſaved, according to <hi>Mat</hi> 11.28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 55.7. alſo 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1, <hi>v.</hi> 15. hee hereupon brake out. I ſee my ſelf undone for ever, without the mercy of God in Chriſts blood. I know not whether to go but to Chriſt, [but intermixing interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively] is there mercy for me? Is there hope for ſuch a one as I am? well, I will adventure my ſoule upon this foundation, I am reſolved I will truſt and hang here, [adding that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Phraſe] I can but periſh, I can but dye, and if I do, it ſhall be in truſting upon Gods grace and Chriſts righteouſneſs, but I will hold faſt that word, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. he hath ſaid thoſe that come, <hi>I will in no wiſe caſt out:</hi> I do come to him, and I will cleave to him; ſurely he will not caſt me off. I told him that upon this Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ground, he might ſoundly and ſurely ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to himſelf comfort; and if his repentance and faith (thus farr) were but ſincere, he might aſſuredly conclude upon the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and truth of his Goſpell that he ſhould be ſaved, the which I endeavored to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170235:54"/>make plaine and practicable to him alſo.</p>
            <p>The Lord was pleaſed ſo wonderfully to enable him by his ſpirit to lay hold upon, and embrace theſe conſiderations, that his heart was filled with Joy and Peace through be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, in ſo much that he was in ſuch a brearhing panting Extaſy, that he put his hands upon his ſides, and cryed out, Oh my heart will break! is there hope for me? is there ſalvation for me? Oh what comfort is this, I never felt nor taſted the like before! I formerly thought there was no comfort but in my ſinfull way, nor no joy but in ſinfull pleaſures, with much more the like; and to the amazement of ſeveral perſons preſent.</p>
            <p>But in the midſt of this Joy, correcting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he breaks out, Oh what is become of the ſoule of him I have murthered, to whom I gave no ſpace to repent! I told him that was indeed a high aggravation of his ſin, and therefore ſhould be improved to humble him the more; but withall, the ſtate of the others ſoule was to him a ſecret, and all his diſtracting thoughts about it, would contribute nothing to the other or himſelf; and therefore that he ſhould ſpend the reſt of his time and thoughts about his own ſoule: finally and principally, <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> might as well have had
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170235:55"/>doubtfull thoughts about the multitudes of ſoules, whoſe Innocent blood he ſhed in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> but this hindred not his pardon. Oh ſaith he, what a mercy is it that I have ſpace to repent, that I was not ſerved as I ſerved him! I might have eſcaped apprehenſion, and ſome way or other have died ſuddenly in my ſins. He took much notice of the patience of God, and of the tenderneſs of the Lord Major, from whoſe viſits and Inſtructions he had reapt much benefit alſo, that his ſouls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was ſo much upon the hearts of ſuch who knew the weight of ſin, and the worth of a ſoule, to be inſtant with God for him.</p>
            <p>Oh but ſaith he, I am afraid of Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leſt I ſhould take comfort too ſoon. I told him that as a perſon might be preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in crying peace, whiles going on in ſin; ſo might he, if he were not ſincere and ſound in his repentance, and faith: but if that were true, he could not be preſumptuous in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and applying the promiſe of the Goſpel to himſelfe; nor on the other hand could he preſume too farr in coming to and reſting upon the grace of God in Chriſt, but the more he did, the more accepted. He ſaid, I am ſure I am humbled for my ſins, as in the ſight of God, and I would be more; I do abhor my
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170235:55"/>ſelfe and my ſin, that if I had oportunity I durſt not commit ſin againſt ſo good a God to offend and diſhonor him; and mentioning that Text. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.20.21. my heart doth not condeme mee of hypocriſy in this; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hiis heart was greatly raiſed again to a ſtrong confidence in God. I do hope, ſaith he, (according to that word <hi>Phil</hi> 1.6.) that God hath begun this work and will performe it to the day of Jeſus Chriſt: and whiles I do live, I will truſt in him, and ſeek to him, and yet not reſt on any thing. Some Papiſts have come (ſaith he) &amp; told me I muſt be a Roman Catholick, or no ſalvation; but alas what works have I to reſt upon, but my murder and my other many evil workes before, that would ſink me for ever, but for the mercy of God on which I truſt! Others doubt, ſaith he, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble; but alas what wil that availe me now? the Lord knows, I do diſcover what I can of perſons and their ſins, that I may do the utmoſt good I can in preventing ſin againſt God, and the ruine of others ſoules: and I have a heart to do more if I could for God before I dye.</p>
            <p>Finally he expreſt much bope and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort &amp; joy ſeveral times in a panting breathing manner, and that Mr. <hi>Yearwood</hi> had been an inſtrument of great refreſhment to him in his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170235:56"/>frequent Viſits; to whom I refer the Reader for a more perfect Narrative; he oft expreſt not only his willingneſs, but deſire to dye, both becauſe of that juſt law of God, [blood for blood] and becauſe he had ſuch good hope through grace, that his ſin and ſorrow ſhould both have an end, much admiring at his gift of memory to retain all ſpoken to him, and alſo wondring at the change in his heart, &amp; his comforts &amp; joys, as being new ſtrange things to him, greatly wondring and magnifying God that he ſhould take the occaſion upon this his moſt foule ſin, to bring him to a ſight of all other ſins and ſave his ſoul. The Lord grant it may have the like effect on others in the ſame pernicious pathes; and that eſpecially yong men may hear and fear, and be converted and healed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:56"/>
            <head>A SERIOUS ADVICE TO THE CITIZENS OF LONDON, By ſome MINISTERS of the GOSPEL in the ſaid CITY: Upon occaſion of the HORRID MURDER And DREADFUL DEATH OF <hi>NATHANIEL BUTLER,</hi> An high Malefactor</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS we thought it a great duty lying upon us, before the execution of the ſentence of death upon <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> to lay out
<pb facs="tcp:170235:57"/>our ſelves to the utmoſt for the promoting of his ſpiritual and eternal good; in frequent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, in conſtant praying for him; in endevouring to convince him of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative greatneſs of his ſins, and in ſpreading of the freeneſs of the grace of God in Chriſt before him, according to the penitential work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, we obſerved in him. So (having done our duty to him, (who is dead under the ſtroke of juſtice) and as we hope with ſome ſucceſs too through the grace of God, for which we bleſs him) we humbly judge there is a further duty incumbent upon us, unto you the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this famous City, who have been ſpectators of this Tragedy, in a ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending of this providence to you and the duty which it calls for.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 9 16. <hi>The Lord is known by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he executeth.</hi> And ſurely this latter Age (though an Age full of ſin) hath not ſet before you a more dreadful inſtance of mans ſinfulneſs, and Gods juſtice (though in the end ſweetned much with mercy) then that which in and upon this notorious Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor hath been laid before your obſervation. And therefore we cannot here be ſilent, but muſt take this advantage with all humility and affection to your ſouls good, plainly to open our hearts to you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:57"/>
            <p>By ſome (we know before hand) we ſhall be ſlighted and cenſured as men too buſy, and may be, as men too credulous; but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God we can ſay, our aim is publick good and the diſcharge of our conſciences, and therefore we are not diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>And we are not wholly without hope, but that ſome benefit may be reaped from theſe few lines, which here with all ſincerity we do preſent upon that late providence which hath been before you.</p>
            <p>Exod. 14.20. That providence we ſay, which like the <hi>Cloud</hi> is on one ſide very dark, on the other ſide very bright; very dark as to mans ſin, very bright as to Gods mercy.</p>
            <p>Tis the daily and inward grief of our ſpirits, God knows it, that our Miniſtry is ſo ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that we ſee ſo little fruit of the word preached by us, that in a City where there is ſuch plain and powerful preaching, ſuch horrid ſins ſhould be committed; Ezek. 19.14. <hi>This is a lamentation and ſhall be for a lamentation.</hi> But poſſibly ſome ſecure ſinners may be a little ſtartled and awakened by this terrible judicial hand of God; and ſo a word ſetting in with this providence may be more effectual then many in an ordinance. We cannot but comply with the will of God in the uſe of all means for the furtherance of your ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:170235:58"/>And oh! that God would ſo bleſs this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation that you all may <hi>hear and fear and ſin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the ſad occaſion, we will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon that: the hainous murder, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable uncleanneſs, the wicked theft, of which <hi>Nat: Butler</hi> was guilty (of the former but once, which we ſpeak not by way of extenuation; for that's too much, of the two latter very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) as alſo the ſhamefulneſs and dreadfulneſs of his death: theſe we paſs over, as being very well known to all of you. Neither ſhall we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt our ſelves in any narrative of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God upon his heart, during his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and at his execution; (though here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we could ſpeak much as being (for the moſt of us) very often with him in this time, and narrow obſervers of him.) Nor ſhall we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate upon ſome of thoſe great truths of the Goſpel, which this famous inſtance doth lead us to; Namely that ſometimes it pleaſes God in the ſovereignty and prerogative of his grace to ceaze upon the greateſt ſinners; and out of the courſeſt rubbiſh to erect the monuments of his unlimited mercy. 1 Tim. 1.16. The Lord doth ſometimes take the vileſt wretches, and hangs them out as patterns of his infinite love that the freeneſs of his grace may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, and the greateſt of ſinners may be incouraged; but ſtill in the way of
<pb facs="tcp:170235:58"/>
               <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> we do not, we dare not limit the Grace of God, as to exclude this Notorious and Bloody ſinner from it; nay we have good hope, that through the infinite Mercy of the Father, and the All-ſufficient Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Son, he is accepted to eternal Life. Indeed, when we conſider the horribleneſs of his ſin, the greatneſs of his joy, after a ſhort humiliation (yet deep and through we hope) we eaſily conjecture, that ſome will queſtion both the prudence of any publication, and the truth of his Converſion. But we will med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with neither of theſe leaving men to jude of the former and God alone (who ſearches and knows the heart) to judge of the latter.</p>
            <p>Waving therefore all theſe things, our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign and buſineſſe in this application, is to preſs upon you (the inhabitants of this City) to ſome of whom we are more neerly related in our reſpective Charges) the ſeveral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which do naturally reſult from this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>We would exhort you in the firſt place, To be thankful to God for his Reſtraining Grace; which though it be ſhort of his Renewing Grace, yet tis with all thankfulneſs to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued: Oh! bleſs the Lord, who keeps you from thoſe ſins which this poor Wretch was guilty of, that you are not Adulterers, Theeves,
<pb facs="tcp:170235:59"/>nay, Murderers and Malefactors, to be <hi>puniſhed by the Judge;</hi> this is the Lords mercy. 1 Cor. 4.7. <hi>Who makes you to differ from others?</hi> Have not you the ſame Names? Have not you the Seed and Spawn of all wickedneſs in you? And ſhould God leave you to the baſeneſs of your own helliſh hearts, would you not alſo run to all <hi>Exceſs</hi> of ſin, and that with <hi>Greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs too?</hi> When you read over this ſad Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we beſeech you lay your hands upon your hearts, and ſay, What a mercy is it, I was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Murderer</hi> nor the <hi>Murdred!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deſire you to mourne over the crying ſins that are to be found amongſt us. Oh! the Scarlet ſins that ſwarm in <hi>London,</hi> even in <hi>London!</hi> Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Profanation of the Lords Day, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel, and of the Miniſtry thereof; nay, even Blood-guiltineſs is to be found amongſt us! Should not your Souls, like the Soul of Righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> be <hi>vexed</hi> within you for theſe things, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7? Should you not all come up to be <hi>Ezekiel's</hi> mourners, in the remembrance of them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4? Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, conſidering that theſe things are done in times of Reformation, and in a place of Viſion, even in <hi>London,</hi> where the Light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſhines ſo gloriouſly; where the Words is Preached ſo plentifully and powerfully, even
<pb facs="tcp:170235:59"/>there theſe abominations are to be found. Will you not lay them to heart?</p>
            <p>And what reaſon have you to admire the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of God to this <hi>City?</hi> Tis a wonder <hi>London</hi> is not made a <hi>Sodom,</hi> that deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth not ſeize upon your houſes, that you are not all ſwept away with the Beeſome of ſuddain deſtruction, that you are not hung up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gibbet as Spectacles of Gods vengeance to all the Nations round about! What? ſo much provocation, and yet the City to ſtand! Oh the Patience and Long-ſuffering of God! Doubtleſs, if God had not a <hi>Remnant</hi> amongſt you, who ſeek him daily, and fear his Name, you had been laid deſolate long before now. <hi>Iſa</hi> 1 9.</p>
            <p>We need not from hence to ſtir you up to ſubmit to <hi>Government,</hi> and to bleſs God that you live in a place where Laws are Executed. What a <hi>Chaos?</hi> what a Wilderneſs of wild Beaſts ſhould we be, if Malefactors were not puniſhed? What Confuſion, Cruelty, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſneſs, would overſpread all, if by whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws, and the care of good Magiſtrates in the Execution of them, we had not ſome Boundaries ſet to the Luſts of men? whether would the heart of man run, if there were not ſome rein upon it? Tis ſad the Law of God will not keep men from ſin, but ſeeing it will
<pb facs="tcp:170235:60"/>not, tis mercy we have the Laws of Man: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are afraid of the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> which have no ſenſe of <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This great Sinner is repreſented to you as an eminent inſtance of the Grace of God, and ſo we hope he was. Tis very neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we ſhould here inſert a Caveat againſt the abuſing of this Grace of God. How apt are we with the Spider to ſuck Poyſon, where with the Bee we ſhould ſuck Honey? How many will be apt from hence to encourage themſelves in ſin, and to ſay, <hi>Let us ſin, that Grace may abound,</hi> Rom. 6.1. Or, let us ſin, for Grace will abound. Man is not more prone to any thing then to catch at eminent Acts of Grace, and to make that <hi>Fewel</hi> to his <hi>Luſt,</hi> which God intended only to be <hi>Food</hi> to his <hi>Faith.</hi> And never was there any age wherein there was more of this Spirit of Preſumption, then this wherein we live; inſomuch, that upon this very account, ſome of us were very inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think, That 'twas better to have the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this man ſuppreſſed then publiſhed. But ſince providence hath ſo ordered it that it doth ſee the Light, we cannot but annex to it an Antidote againſt preſuming. Sinners, do not pervert this Grace of God; God lets you have it, to keep you off from the rock of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, not that you ſhould run upon the rock
<pb facs="tcp:170235:60"/>of preſumption. Deut. 29.19, 20. If you ſin you may have mercy, but if you preſume to ſin, can you then expect mercy? Grace rejected may yet ſave you (though that will coſt you dear) but oh tremble to abuſe the grace of God to incourage you in ſins!</p>
            <p>God ſometimes gives ſome rare inſtances of his grace to notorious ſinners that none may <hi>deſpair,</hi> but he is very choice in theſe that none may <hi>preſume.</hi> Tis true, upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance the greateſt ſinner ſhall find mercy, but how do you know, that God will give you repentance? How many are in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation that this offender was, that die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch work upon them? we affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately beſeech you and warn you, not to <hi>turn this grace of God into wantonneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things we hint in general; More particularly we ſhall addreſs our ſelves to you in the ſeveral capacities wherein you ſtand.</p>
            <p>You the <hi>Right honourable Magiſtrates of the City,</hi> with all ſubmiſſion, and yet with all boldneſs we exhort you to do your duty. Tis not enough for you to puniſh ſin when 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, but you are to endevour the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, you ſee what is the ſad fruit of <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Whore-houſes,</hi> and ſuch places, we hope your zeal will yet continue, nay be heightned in the ſuppreſſing of them. Down with them,
<pb facs="tcp:170235:61"/>Down with them, ſpare them not; they are the Divels Shops, and let him have no Free-Trade amongſt us: If you will, none ſhall have ſo many Cuſtomers as he. How many Labourers drink that away at theſe houſes, which ſhould maintain their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with bread? How are the youth of this City debaunched at them? where they have their Gaming, Cheating, Whoring; and what not? Oh let your Reformation be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and throughout in this particular! But herein bleſſed be God, we have great cauſe as well to commend as to quicken your zeale. We heartily wiſh that thoſe who have power in the <hi>Suburbs</hi> of the City, would be as active in the reſtraining of ſin as you are; that thoſe places and perſons which you will not indure in the City (the naming of which would ſoul our pen) might not be held up and harboured there; otherwiſe it will be ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to ſmother Whores out of one Hive, when they have another ready to receive them.</p>
            <p>We hear and fear tis too true that Prieſts and Jeſuites (thoſe Romiſh Locuſts) do ſwarm amongſt us in the City and Suburbs: We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt, and for love to the Goſpel, to put forth your power to the utmoſt for the diſcovering &amp; ſuppreſſing of them: And the rather, becauſe they and their
<pb facs="tcp:170235:61"/>party are ſo bold, as to intrude themſelves upon priſoners condemned to die, to pervert them from the true Religion, (for this attempt they were bold to make upon <hi>N. B.</hi> before he was executed.)</p>
            <p>We ſhould alſo ſpeak to our ſelves, and to our <hi>reverend Brethren</hi> in the Miniſtry. Doth not this providence ſpeak ſomething to us? Should we not from hence be ſtirred up in our ſeveral congregations, more vigoruſly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſin, and to deter men from ſin? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſinners go, if we let them alone? Let our preaching be lively, quick, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, by Gods bleſſing, it may be a means to prevent theſe abominable practiſes; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let's do this and then let our hearers do what they will, their <hi>blood ſhall be required at their own hands.</hi> Ezech. 3.18, 19. We ſhall be free from it. Let us beat down drunkenneſs. Adultery, &amp;c. and ſuch ſcandalous ſins; and while we labour to preach down unbelief, let us take heed that preſumption and groſs ſins do not break in upon us with a mighty breach.</p>
            <p>Should we enlarge upon theſe things, we ſhould be tedious. Our principal intendment was to ſpeak a word to you, the people and Citizens of the place which we ſhall diſpatch with all plainneſs and brevity. And here we
<pb facs="tcp:170235:62"/>will only take the liberty of adviſing you in the Notion of <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Governed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You that are <hi>Governours,</hi> (we mean Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of families) give us leave to ſet in with this providence, and to ſtir you up, to make more conſcience of the Family-duties and engagements that lie upon you, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to your children and Servants. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably (if things be not mis-repeſented) had there been a conſciencious diſcharge of theſe duties in the Family, where this young man lived, he had never come to this ſad end. But we had rather awaken then cenſure; Was not that a brave reſolution of <hi>Joſhua? I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Joſh 24.15. Gen. 18.9. Can you have a better Evidence of ſincerity towards God, then a faithful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up to relative and Family-duties? Do not parents that ſend up their children to you, put a great truſt into your hands? Are not their children dearer to them then all their outward comforts, and ſhall they miſcarry under you for want of care? Will not their blood be required at your hands, if they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh through your neglect? will it not be ſad to have children and ſervanns to riſe up in judgment againſt you and to bring in evidence at the great tribunall of Chriſt? <hi>Lord my
<pb facs="tcp:170235:62"/>Father never minded me! Lord my maſter ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver regarded me, I might ſin, he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved me, I might go to hell, it was all one to him,</hi> will not this be ſad? will not this be ſweet to you, when you come to die to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſay, Lord I have <hi>walked in my houſe with a perfect heart?</hi> Pſal. 101.2. Have you no love to religion, to propagate it, and to provide for it's flouriſhing when you are dead and gone? Doth not your neglect of family-duties make all the endeavours of our godly magiſtrates, and of godly miniſters to be ineffectual and fruſtraineous? God hath put it into their hearts to do good, but tis but little, they can do in publick, becauſe you are ſo remiſs in private. And tis the deſire of our ſouls to beat down ſin but we groan under the ſenſe of ſad diſappointment, and this is one reaſon of it, <hi>what we do at the Church is undone by you again in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies;</hi> No ſetting on the word, no pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the word &amp;c. Oh that theſe things might be as ſo many ſpurs in your ſides, to quicken you to family duties.</p>
            <p>Set up prayer in your Families; There's a curſe pronouned upon the Families, that do not call upon God. The Lord be merciful to the thouſands of Families in the City,
<pb facs="tcp:170235:63"/>where there is ſcarce a purger by the maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the family, from yeer to yeer. How can ſuch hope for the bleſſing of God to be upon them, who, though he gives mercy free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet <hi>he will be ſought</hi> unto for it? Ezek. 36.3, 7. How can ſuch look for Gods <hi>bounty,</hi> who deny him his <hi>worſhip?</hi> Doth not <hi>prayer</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all your Family-comforts, and ſanctifie all your family-comforts? <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening</hi> call upon God; and call in your ſervants, let them not want the benefit of prayer; 'twil be poor to <hi>feed</hi> their bodyes, and to <hi>ſtarve</hi> their ſouls. If you <hi>eate</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by all means <hi>pray</hi> together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechize</hi> your children and ſervants; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the fundamentals of religion; would you keep them from error in the Head, from looſneſs in the life, make conſcience of this duty. How excellent, how neceſſary, how profitable is this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and yet how ſadly is it neglected, we may in a great meaſure blame you for the many Hereticks, and erroneous perſons, with whom we ſwarm in theſe dayes.</p>
            <p>Read and open the Scriptures to them, but do this with all humility and ſobriety, or elſe there will be danger. Theſe are the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine, the Treaſury of all knowledge, able to make you and yours wife <hi>to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170235:63"/>Let the <hi>word of Chriſt dwell richly</hi> in you; and in all that belong to you</p>
            <p>See that they frequent the <hi>publick Ordinances</hi> let them follow you to the houſe of God, not out of ſtate, but in love to their ſoules; and when they are there, ſee they keep there, that they do not run out again to <hi>Ale-houſes</hi> and <hi>Taverns</hi> (as too many do, to our grief and your ſhame be it ſpoken) when a publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is ended, call them to an account, ſee what they remember, wherein they profit, how they reliſh the word; this is to do good indeed to their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Keep them to a ſtrict obſervance of the <hi>Lords-day;</hi> you will not let them trifle away your day, then you'l hold them to their work; Oh! let them not trifle away the Lords day. Why do your children and ſervants ſtand gaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at your doors upon the Sabbath? Call them in, put them upon reading wholſom books, and other exerciſes which are proper to the day; be not partakers of their ſin.</p>
            <p>What ever liberty you grant them at other times, hold them to a cloſe ſanctification of the Sabbath. And ſpend this day with them, in <hi>prayer, repetition, ſinging of Pſalms;</hi> This is to make your Families as ſo many <hi>little Churches</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. How little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience do the generality of you make of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb facs="tcp:170235:64"/>bath-duty; we might ſadly bemoan this before the Lord. For your ſelves you can make that day which is a day for Phyſick for the ſoul, to be the Day for Phyſick for the Body; you cannot ſpare time all the weeke long, you'l take it upon the Lords day. And for your children and ſervants, let them walk in the Field, play in the ſtreets, ſleep in their beds, or drink in Taverns, 'tis all one to you! Will God beare this from you? Certainly, this will be bitterneſs in the end.</p>
            <p>Do not indulge your ſervants in <hi>idleneſs,</hi> that is the bane of youth, the Devils in-let to all temptations.</p>
            <p>An idle perſon is like tinder that will take every ſparke that falls upon it, let them be out of imployment, 'tis a thouſand to one, but preſently they are in ſome ſin. And yet thoſe that know how to uſe their Liberty, let them have it ſometimes for lawful recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, but this we leave to your pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>In the purſuit of your own pleaſures and conveniences have a care of your Families; Many of you go to your Country houſes (we condemne you not for it) but what becomes of your ſervants? As <hi>Eliab</hi> ſaid to <hi>David, with whom have you left</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170235:64"/>thoſe few ſheep in the wilderneſs? Whilſt you are in your pleaſant gardens gratifying your ſelves in your creature-enjoyments, who takes care of them that are left behind to pray with them, to inſtruct them, to ſee they ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the Sabbath; the health of ſome Maſters bodies is the ruine of their ſervants ſouls.</p>
            <p>Set them in all things a good example, if they ſee you can ſtrain in defraunding others, they'l eaſily come to ſtrain in the defrauding of you; let them ſee you fear to ſin and that will be an awe upon their ſpirits againſt ſin.</p>
            <p>Take your Apprentices out of religious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in the Country; Many of you are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with vexatious ſervants, you may thank your ſelves for it; you take your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices by the pound, not by good education, who will give moſt, not who will deſerve moſt, and you ſmart for it afterwards.</p>
            <p>But how do theſe Heads ſwell upon our hearts, though we do but name them! Theſe are ſome of the things which we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the ſerious conſideration of you, who are <hi>Governours</hi> Families; and the Lord make them uſeful to you.</p>
            <p>In particular, it is of great uſe to prevent much wickedneſs to look to the keys and doors of your houſes and to have them in your own cuſtody not in your ſervants that ſo an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinning may be cut off from thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:170235:65"/>ſeek ſuch occaſions as moſt fit for their pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſigns,</p>
            <p>Keep up Diſcipline, or rather reſtore it again; How is it fallen in theſe times, how is it almoſt loſt amongſt us in the City; The reins which your predeceſſors held with a very ſtrict hand, are very looſe in yours; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your ſervants will do what they liſt, and you let them alone; we do very much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the low ebb of Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and judg that to be one Cauſe of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſorders which are among us; we heartily wiſh it may be reſtored in Church, in State, in Families, if this be wanting, all things run up to ſtrange confuſion.</p>
            <p>A Word to the Youth and <hi>Apprentices</hi> of this City, and we have done. Oh that you would hear us now, leaſt you <hi>mourne</hi> at the laſt, and ſay, <hi>How have we hated inſtruction, and our hearts deſpiſed reproof? And have not obeyed the voice of our Teachers, nor inclined our car to them that inſtructed us.</hi> This <hi>Great Offendor</hi> was one of your Rank, had he taken the advice of Gods Word, his ſin had not been ſo great, nor his puniſhment ſo terrible. Of all, we fear, our counſel to you will be the moſt ſucceſsleſs; Youth is raſh, inconfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ate vain proud, but ſometime or other you will remember what we ſay.</p>
            <p>Take heed of <hi>leſſer ſins.</hi> Little ſins will
<pb facs="tcp:170235:65"/>make way for greater ſins; if you ſip of ſin, youll be drunk of it at laſt. How modeſt is ſin at firſt, but when 'tis gratified, it growes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent. This poor man lately executed, firſt he began to game, then to ſteal, then to Whore, and then to Murder.</p>
            <p>Be careful of your company: aſſociate with them that fear God; ſay unto them that are vain and wicked, <hi>Depart from us, for We will keep the Commandments of God,</hi> Pſal. 119.115. Bad company is the way to corrupt and ſpoil you: <hi>Can a man touch pitch, and not be defiled?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read the Scriptures much; by them you muſt ſtand or fall to all eternity; when we walk by you in your Shops, we ſee many have their Play-Book in their hands, but few have the <hi>Bible</hi> in their hands; the Shop-Book is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, but the Bible is ſhut.</p>
            <p>Entertain high thoughts of Holineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men: The froth of your wits runs out too often in jeering godlineſſe; but take heed, thats not a thing to be ſo dealt withal. Many of you count ſin to be gallantry, and Religion but a low and diſgraceful thing. God convince you of your folly.</p>
            <p>Frequent Publick Ordinances, eſpecially upon the Lords day, becauſe you have not opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſo to do upon the week days. You'l find more comfort in the Word and Prayer, then in all your youthful delights.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170235:66"/>
            <p>Keep the Sabbath; You, have ſix dayes, let God have one; can he have leſſe? God out of ſpecial reſpects to ſervants, hath inſtituted and ſanctified this day. How can you hope to keep an everlaſting Sabbath in heaven, if this Sabbath on earth be profaned by you. Many go to Tiburn lamenting the profanation of the Lords day, as that which uſhered in all their wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Every day ſpend ſome time in private pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; 'tis but riſing a little the earlyer, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed a little the later; you ſhall never be the worſe for that time you ſpend in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</p>
            <p>Be, ſubject and obedient to your Maſters; ſtudy how to pleaſe them; bear with their paſſionate infirmities: <hi>Do not purloyn but ſhew all good fidelity, that the doctrine of God our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour may be adorned,</hi> Tit. 2.9, 10. Be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in your Callings; if you be idle, Satan will get an advantage. The ſitting bird is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhot, and the ſtanding water gathers filth.</p>
            <p>Love thoſe that curb you, and reſtrain you in wayes of ſin; they are your beſt friends: 'tis better to beheld in, then to have a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed liberty; 'tis better to have luſt reſtrained then ſatisfied. Be not angry with thoſe who cannot ſee you damne your ſouls, and let you alone.</p>
            <p>Enter upon the wayes of God betimes, the
<pb facs="tcp:170235:66"/>ſooner the better: Shall the devil have the beſt draught, and ſhall God be put off with the Lees and Dregs: <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1.</p>
            <p>Live alwayes as in Gods ſight, and know, if you ſin, God will certainly ſind you out one time or other. Alas how many wayes hath God to bring the moſt hidden works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to light; ſometimes by ſtartling mens own conſciences to an accuſation of themſelvs, ſometimes by awakening ſome of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices to the diſcovery of the reſt. If you ſin together, you ſhall ſmart together. Let this ſad example never be forgotten by you for this: Thoſe that were Confederates in ſin, are made inſtruments and occaſions of miſery each to other. Look not upon ſin in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it, but in the danger of it: The Wine ſparkles in the cup, but 'twill be poyſon in the belly. Fear the ſtrokes of God more then the ſtroaks of man; What's a fetter, a dungeon, a gallows to hell fire? Mortifie a ſpirit of pride Never ſuch pride amongſt the youth of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as now; What vanity in apparel, what ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perciliouſneſs in carriage, what contempt of Authority? Oh, <hi>be clothed with humility,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.5. Give not way to imaginaay, ſpeculative heart ſins; Murder in the heart, will ſoon be Murder in the hand; uncleanneſs allowed in the thoughts, wil come to bodily uncleanneſs at the
<pb facs="tcp:170235:67"/>laſt. Keep Satan at a diſtaace, if he get in, he'l be too hard for you</p>
            <p>To ſum up all: A dreadful ſpectacle of Gods Juſtice, and of the fruit of ſin, bath been lately ſet before you, we beſeech you in the Bowels of Jeſus Chriſt, break off from all your ſinful wayes by repentance; <hi>One</hi> is ſmitten that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> may fear; He's a warning to you, take heed leſt you be made a warning unto others. If you would avoid his <hi>end,</hi> walk not in his <hi>ſins;</hi> as ſecure as you are, if you will allow your ſelves in that which is evil, you do not know whither the divel wil carry you in a way of ſin, or to what God will bring you in a way of punſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Stand in aw therefore and ſin not,</hi> Pſ. 4.4. <hi>Flee youthful luſts,</hi> 2. Tim. 2.22. <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he ſal,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.12. Every day pray that God will keep you from and ſtrengthen you againſt temptation: Say not, 'tis not poſſible I ſhould ever be ſo vile as this Malefactor was; Alas, if God leave you you'l be as bad as he. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth alwayes.</hi> Prov. 28.14. In all things ſo carry your ſelves according to the rule of the Word, that you may neither fall into the hands of men, nor into the hands of God, which is far the moſt dreadful. <hi>'Tis a fearful thing to fal into the hands of the living God.</hi> Heb. 10.31.</p>
            <p>That Governors and Governed may thus diſcharge their duties ſhall be the great deſign
<pb facs="tcp:170235:67"/>of our Miniſtrie by Gods aſſiſtance, and our conſtant prayer at the Throne of Grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Septemb.</hi> 11. 1657.</date>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edmund Calamy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arthur Jackſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Nalton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Jacomb,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Hutchiſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas White.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Parſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Doelittle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simeon Aſhe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Caſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Taylor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roger Drake.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Griffith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthew Poole.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dan. Batcheler.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
